<dataset>
    <name>Cell Collective</name>
    <description>Interactive Modelling of Biological Networks</description>
    <contact>support@cellcollective.org</contact>
    <url>https://cellcollective.org</url>
    <release>None</release>
    <release_date/>
    <entry_count>77</entry_count>
    <entries>
                    <entry id="2309">
                <name>EGFR &amp; ErbB Signaling</name>
                <description>The epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) signaling pathway is probably the best-studied receptor system in mammalian cells, and it also has become a popular example for employing mathematical modeling to cellular signaling networks. Dynamic models have the highest explanatory and predictive potential; however, the lack of kinetic information restricts current models of EGFR signaling to smaller sub-networks. This work aims to provide a large-scale qualitative model that comprises the main and also the side routes of EGFR/ErbB signaling and that still enables one to derive important functional properties and predictions. Using a recently introduced logical modeling framework, we first examined general topological properties and the qualitative stimulus-response behavior of the network. With species equivalence classes, we introduce a new technique for logical networks that reveals sets of nodes strongly coupled in their behavior. We also analyzed a model variant which explicitly accounts for uncertainties regarding the logical combination of signals in the model. The predictive power of this model is still high, indicating highly redundant sub-structures in the network. Finally, one key advance of this work is the introduction of new techniques for assessing high-throughput data with logical models (and their underlying interaction graph). By employing these techniques for phospho-proteomic data from primary hepatocytes and the HepG2 cell line, we demonstrate that our approach enables one to uncover inconsistencies between experimental results and our current qualitative knowledge and to generate new hypotheses and conclusions. Our results strongly suggest that the Rac/Cdc42 induced p38 and JNK cascades are independent of PI3K in both primary hepatocytes and HepG2. Furthermore, we detected that the activation of JNK in response to neuregulin follows a PI3K-dependent signaling pathway.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2309:1/egfr-&amp;-erbb-signaling</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-12-19"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2018-04-15 09:15:58"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-12-19 18:12:48</field>
                    <field name="model_score">56.6652</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="5128">
                <name>Lac Operon</name>
                <description>Our model includes the two main glucose control mechanisms of catabolite repression and inducer exclusion. We show that this Boolean model is capable of predicting the ON and OFF steady states and bistability. Further, we present a reduced model which shows that lac mRNA and lactose form the core of the lac operon, and that this reduced model exhibits the same dynamics.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#5128:1/lac-operon</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2016-11-08"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-12-19 15:58:31"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2016-11-08 10:38:26</field>
                    <field name="model_score">18.7209</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2314">
                <name>IL-6 Signalling</name>
                <description>The pro-inflammatory cytokines interleukin 1 (IL-1) and 6 (IL-6) are crucially involved in the regulation of a multitude of physiological processes, in particular coordinating the immune response upon bacterial infection and tissue injury. Both interleukins induce complex signalling cascades and trigger the production of mitogenic, pro-proliferative, anti-apoptotic, chemotactic, and pro-angiogenic factors thereby affecting the delicate balance between regenerationvs. invasive growth, tumourigenesis and metastasis. Moreover, several links to insulin resistance have been found within their associated signalling networks. Focusing on this from a systems biology perspective, we introduce comprehensive large-scale network models of IL-1 and IL-6 signalling which are based on a logical modelling approach and reflect the current biological knowledge. Theoretical network analysis enabled us to uncover general topological features and to make testable predictions on the stimulus-response behaviour of the networks. In this context, non-intuitive network-wide species dependencies as well as structures of regulatory feedback and feed-forward mechanisms could be characterised. By integrating high-throughput phosphoproteomic data from primary human hepatocytes we optimised the model structures to obtain models with high prediction accuracy for hepatocytes. Our model-based data analysis, for instance, suggested model modifications regarding (i) Akt contribution to IL-1-stimulated p38 MAPK activation and (ii) insignificant p38 MAPK activation in response to IL-6. In light of the presented results and in conjunction with the detailed model documentations, both models hold great potential for theoretical studies and practical applications.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2314:1/il6-signalling</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2014-01-11"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-05-18 14:36:14"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2014-01-11 00:01:02</field>
                    <field name="model_score">32.0165</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="1557">
                <name>Signal Transduction in Fibroblasts</name>
                <description>This model represents a set of generic, commonly expressed receptor signaling pathways, including EGFR, G-protein-coupled receptor (alpha i, alpha q, alpha 12/13, and alpha s ligands), integrin, and stress pathways.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#1557:1/signal-transduction-in-fibroblasts</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2011-06-06"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-11-29 12:07:57"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2011-06-06 19:53:13</field>
                    <field name="model_score">52.3185</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="6678">
                <name>CD4+ T cell Differentiation</name>
                <description>The model includes 38 components and 96 biochemical interactions that regulate the differentiation process of major T cell subtypes, i.e., Th1, Th2, Th17 and iTreg cells. Individual components of the model represent lineage-specifying transcription factors (Tbet, GATA3, ROR&#947;t, and Foxp3), STAT proteins, cytokines, their receptors, and other signaling molecules. The extracellular environment is represented in the model by eight cytokines and a (generic) TCR ligand known to play a role in T cell differentiation. PMID: 22871178</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#6678:1/cd4+-t-cell-differentiation</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2017-02-16"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2018-04-12 16:18:24"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">CD4+ T cell differentiation.</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2017-02-16 12:52:40</field>
                    <field name="model_score">226.8538</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2329">
                <name>Apoptosis Network</name>
                <description>To understand the design principles of the molecular interaction network associated with the irreversibility of cell apoptosis and the stability of cell surviving, we constructed a Boolean network integrating both the intrinsic and extrinsic pro-apoptotic pathways with pro-survival signal transduction pathways. We performed statistical analyses of the dependences of cell fate on initial states and on input signals. The analyses reproduced the well-known pro- and anti-apoptotic effects of key external signals and network components. We found that the external GF signal by itself did not change the apoptotic ratio from randomly chosen initial states when there is no external TNF signal, but can significantly offset apoptosis induced by the TNF signal. While a complete model produces the expected irreversibility of the apoptosis process, alternative models missing one or more of four selected inter-component connections indicate that the feedback loops directly involving the caspase 3 are essential for maintaining irreversibility of apoptosis. The feedback loops involving P53 showed compensating effects when those involving caspase 3 have been removed. The GF signal significantly increases the stability of the surviving states of the network. The apoptosis network seems to use different modules by design to control the irreversibility of the apoptosis process and the stability of the surviving states. Such a design may accommodate the needed plasticity for the network to adapt to different cellular environments: depending on the strength of external pro-surviving signals, apoptosis can be induced either easily or difficultly by pro-apoptotic signal of varying strengths, but proceed with invariable irreversibility.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2329:1/apoptosis-network</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2014-02-01"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-10-13 16:16:10"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2014-02-01 14:41:22</field>
                    <field name="model_score">159.5993</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="8227">
                <name>T-LGL Survival Network 2011 Reduced Network</name>
                <description>The blood cancer T cell large granular lymphocyte (T-LGL) leukemia is a chronic disease characterized by a clonal proliferation of cytotoxic T cells. As no curative therapy is yet known for this disease, identification of potential therapeutic targets is of immense importance. In this paper, we perform a comprehensive dynamical and structural analysis of a network model of this disease. By employing a network reduction technique, we identify the stationary states (fixed points) of the system, representing normal and diseased (T-LGL) behavior, and analyze their precursor states (basins of attraction) using an asynchronous Boolean dynamic framework. This analysis identifies the T-LGL states of 54 components of the network, out of which 36 (67%) are corroborated by previous experimental evidence and the rest are novel predictions. We further test and validate one of these newly identified states experimentally. Specifically, we verify the prediction that the node SMAD is over-active in leukemic T-LGL by demonstrating the predominant phosphorylation of the SMAD family members Smad2 and Smad3. Our systematic perturbation analysis using dynamical and structural methods leads to the identification of 19 potential therapeutic targets, 68% of which are corroborated by experimental evidence. The novel therapeutic targets provide valuable guidance for wet-bench experiments. In addition, we successfully identify two new candidates for engineering long-lived T cells necessary for the delivery of virus and cancer vaccines. Overall, this study provides a bird's-eye-view of the avenues available for identification of therapeutic targets for similar diseases through perturbation of the underlying signal transduction network.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#8227:1/tlgl-survival-network-2011-reduced-network</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2017-07-20"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-07-20 16:59:45"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2017-07-20 11:02:32</field>
                    <field name="model_score">5.8204</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2084">
                <name>Death Receptor Signaling</name>
                <description>Cytokines such as TNF and FASL can trigger death or survival depending on cell lines and cellular conditions. The mechanistic details of how a cell chooses among these cell fates are still unclear. The understanding of these processes is important since they are altered in many diseases, including cancer and AIDS. Using a discrete modelling formalism, we present a mathematical model of cell fate decision recapitulating and integrating the most consistent facts extracted from the literature. This model provides a generic high-level view of the interplays between NFkappaB pro-survival pathway, RIP1-dependent necrosis, and the apoptosis pathway in response to death receptor-mediated signals. Wild type simulations demonstrate robust segregation of cellular responses to receptor engagement. Model simulations recapitulate documented phenotypes of protein knockdowns and enable the prediction of the effects of novel knockdowns. In silico experiments simulate the outcomes following ligand removal at different stages, and suggest experimental approaches to further validate and specialise the model for particular cell types. We also propose a reduced conceptual model implementing the logic of the decision process. This analysis gives specific predictions regarding cross-talks between the three pathways, as well as the transient role of RIP1 protein in necrosis, and confirms the phenotypes of novel perturbations. Our wild type and mutant simulations provide novel insights to restore apoptosis in defective cells. The model analysis expands our understanding of how cell fate decision is made. Moreover, our current model can be used to assess contradictory or controversial data from the literature. Ultimately, it constitutes a valuable reasoning tool to delineate novel experiments.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2084:1/death-receptor-signaling</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-04-15"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-04-15 10:28:57</field>
                    <field name="model_score">42.8818</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2341">
                <name>Body Segmentation in Drosophila 2013</name>
                <description>Drosophila melanogaster, body segmentation</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2341:1/body-segmentation-in-drosophila-2013</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2014-02-17"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-07-19 12:29:55"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2014-02-17 13:34:20</field>
                    <field name="model_score">9.201600000000001</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="1582">
                <name>Signaling in Macrophage Activation</name>
                <description> BACKGROUND: The complex yet flexible cellular response to pathogens is orchestrated by the interaction of multiple signalling and metabolic pathways. The molecular regulation of this response has been studied in great detail but comprehensive and unambiguous diagrams describing these events are generally unavailable. Four key signalling cascades triggered early-on in the innate immune response are the toll-like receptor, interferon, NF-kappaB and apoptotic pathways, which co-operate to defend cells against a given pathogen. However, these pathways are commonly viewed as separate entities rather than an integrated network of molecular interactions. RESULTS: Here we describe the construction of a logically represented pathway diagram which attempts to integrate these four pathways central to innate immunity using a modified version of the Edinburgh Pathway Notation. The pathway map is available in a number of electronic formats and editing is supported by yEd graph editor software. CONCLUSION: The map presents a powerful visual aid for interpreting the available pathway interaction knowledge and underscores the valuable contribution well constructed pathway diagrams make to communicating large amounts of molecular interaction data. Furthermore, we discuss issues with the limitations and scalability of pathways presented in this fashion, explore options for automated layout of large pathway networks and demonstrate how such maps can aid the interpretation of functional studies.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#1582:1/signaling-in-macrophage-activation</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2011-09-06"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2011-09-06 15:26:55</field>
                    <field name="model_score">41.5316</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="7984">
                <name>MAPK Cancer Cell Fate Network</name>
                <description>The Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase (MAPK) network consists of tightly interconnected signalling pathways involved in diverse cellular processes, such as cell cycle, survival, apoptosis and differentiation. Although several studies reported the involvement of these signalling cascades in cancer deregulations, the precise mechanisms underlying their influence on the balance between cell proliferation and cell death (cell fate decision) in pathological circumstances remain elusive. Based on an extensive analysis of published data, we have built a comprehensive and generic reaction map for the MAPK signalling network, using CellDesigner software. In order to explore the MAPK responses to different stimuli and better understand their contributions to cell fate decision, we have considered the most crucial components and interactions and encoded them into a logical model, using the software GINsim. Our logical model analysis particularly focuses on urinary bladder cancer, where MAPK network deregulations have often been associated with specific phenotypes. To cope with the combinatorial explosion of the number of states, we have applied novel algorithms for model reduction and for the compression of state transition graphs, both implemented into the software GINsim. The results of systematic simulations for different signal combinations and network perturbations were found globally coherent with published data. In silico experiments further enabled us to delineate the roles of specific components, cross-talks and regulatory feedbacks in cell fate decision. Finally, tentative proliferative or anti-proliferative mechanisms can be connected with established bladder cancer deregulations, namely Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor (EGFR) over-expression and Fibroblast Growth Factor Receptor 3 (FGFR3) activating mutations.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#7984:1/mapk-cancer-cell-fate-network</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2017-04-28"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-07-25 20:06:24"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2017-04-28 15:06:55</field>
                    <field name="model_score">19.8</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="4932">
                <name>Stomatal Opening Model</name>
                <description>Analyzing the long-term behaviors (attractors) of dynamic models of biological systems can provide valuable insight into biological phenotypes and their stability. In this paper we identify the allowed long-term behaviors of a multi-level, 70-node dynamic model of the stomatal opening process in plants. We start by reducing the model&#8217;s huge state space. We first reduce unregulated nodes and simple mediator nodes, then simplify the regulatory functions of selected nodes while keeping the model consistent with experimental observations. We perform attractor analysis on the resulting 32-node reduced model by two methods: 1. converting it into a Boolean model, then applying two attractor-finding algorithms; 2. theoretical analysis of the regulatory functions. We further demonstrate the robustness of signal propagation by showing that a large percentage of single-node knockouts does not affect the stomatal opening level. Combining both methods with analysis of perturbation scenarios, we conclude that all nodes except two in the reduced model have a single attractor; and only two nodes can admit oscillations. The multistability or oscillations of these four nodes do not affect the stomatal opening level in any situation. This conclusion applies to the original model as well in all the biologically meaningful cases. In addition, the stomatal opening level is resilient against single-node knockouts. Thus, we conclude that the complex structure of this signal transduction network provides multiple information propagation pathways while not allowing extensive multistability or oscillations, resulting in robust signal propagation. Our innovative combination of methods offers a promising way to analyze multi-level models.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#4932:1/stomatal-opening-model</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2016-10-01"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2018-03-20 10:10:01"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2016-10-01 13:20:49</field>
                    <field name="model_score">88.7</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="1607">
                <name>Mammalian Cell Cycle</name>
                <description>BACKGROUND: In breast cancer, overexpression of the transmembrane tyrosine kinase ERBB2 is an adverse prognostic marker, and occurs in almost 30% of the patients. For therapeutic intervention, ERBB2 is targeted by monoclonal antibody trastuzumab in adjuvant settings; however, de novo resistance to this antibody is still a serious issue, requiring the identification of additional targets to overcome resistance. In this study, we have combined computational simulations, experimental testing of simulation results, and finally reverse engineering of a protein interaction network to define potential therapeutic strategies for de novo trastuzumab resistant breast cancer. RESULTS: First, we employed Boolean logic to model regulatory interactions and simulated single and multiple protein loss-of-functions. Then, our simulation results were tested experimentally by producing single and double knockdowns of the network components and measuring their effects on G1/S transition during cell cycle progression. Combinatorial targeting of ERBB2 and EGFR did not affect the response to trastuzumab in de novo resistant cells, which might be due to decoupling of receptor activation and cell cycle progression. Furthermore, examination of c-MYC in resistant as well as in sensitive cell lines, using a specific chemical inhibitor of c-MYC (alone or in combination with trastuzumab), demonstrated that both trastuzumab sensitive and resistant cells responded to c-MYC perturbation. CONCLUSION: In this study, we connected ERBB signaling with G1/S transition of the cell cycle via two major cell signaling pathways and two key transcription factors, to model an interaction network that allows for the identification of novel targets in the treatment of trastuzumab resistant breast cancer. Applying this new strategy, we found that, in contrast to trastuzumab sensitive breast cancer cells, combinatorial targeting of ERBB receptors or of key signaling intermediates does not have potential for treatment of de novo trastuzumab resistant cells. Instead, c-MYC was identified as a novel potential target protein in breast cancer cells.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#1607:1/mammalian-cell-cycle</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2011-10-19"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2018-06-07 11:22:45"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2011-10-19 10:49:22</field>
                    <field name="model_score">51.3724</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="4942">
                <name>Pro-inflammatory Tumor Microenvironment in Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</name>
                <description>Lineage fate decisions of hematopoietic cells depend on intrinsic factors and extrinsic signals provided by the bone marrow microenvironment, where they reside. Abnormalities in composition and function of hematopoietic niches have been proposed as key contributors of acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) progression. Our previous experimental findings strongly suggest that pro-inflammatory cues contribute to mesenchymal niche abnormalities that result in maintenance of ALL precursor cells at the expense of normal hematopoiesis. Here, we propose a molecular regulatory network interconnecting the major communication pathways between hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells (HSPCs) and mesenchymal stromal cells (MSCs) within the BM. Dynamical analysis of the network as a Boolean model reveals two stationary states that can be interpreted as the intercellular contact status. Furthermore, simulations describe the molecular patterns observed during experimental proliferation and activation. Importantly, our model predicts instability in the CXCR4/CXCL12 and VLA4/VCAM1 interactions following microenvironmental perturbation due by temporal signaling from Toll like receptors (TLRs) ligation. Therefore, aberrant expression of NF-&#954;B induced by intrinsic or extrinsic factors may contribute to create a tumor microenvironment where a negative feedback loop inhibiting CXCR4/CXCL12 and VLA4/VCAM1 cellular communication axes allows for the maintenance of malignant cells.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#4942:1/proinflammatory-tumor-microenvironment-in-acute-lymphoblastic-leukemia</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2016-10-06"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-03-31 14:40:05"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2016-10-06 11:06:43</field>
                    <field name="model_score">14.4807</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2901">
                <name>T cell differentiation</name>
                <description>Regulatory network governing the differentiation of CD4+ T cells.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2901:1/t-cell-differentiation</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2015-06-03"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-27 19:10:25"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2015-06-03 09:30:44</field>
                    <field name="model_score">47.07710000000001</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2135">
                <name>Yeast Apoptosis</name>
                <description>Programmed cell death (PCD) is an essential cellular mechanism that is evolutionary conserved, mediated through various pathways and acts by integrating different stimuli. Many diseases such as neurodegenerative diseases and cancers are found to be caused by, or associated with, regulations in the cell death pathways. Yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae, is a unicellular eukaryotic organism that shares with human cells components and pathways of the PCD and is therefore used as a model organism. Boolean modeling is becoming promising approach to capture qualitative behavior and describe essential properties of such complex networks. Here we present large literature-based and to our knowledge first Boolean model that combines pathways leading to apoptosis (a type of PCD) in yeast. Analysis of the yeast model confirmed experimental findings of anti-apoptotic role of Bir1p and pro-apoptotic role of Stm1p and revealed activation of the stress protein kinase Hog proposing the maximal level of activation upon heat stress. In addition we extended the yeast model and created an in silico humanized yeast in which human pro- and anti-apoptotic regulators Bcl-2 family and Valosin-contain protein (VCP) are included in the model. We showed that accumulation of Bax in silico humanized yeast shows apoptotic markers and that VCP is essential target of Akt Signaling. The presented Boolean model provides comprehensive description of yeast apoptosis network behavior. Extended model of humanized yeast gives new insights of how complex human disease like neurodegeneration can initially be tested.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2135:1/yeast-apoptosis</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-06-04"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2018-04-18 22:38:10"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-06-04 15:10:00</field>
                    <field name="model_score">47.961000000000006</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="11863">
                <name>Senescence Associated Secretory Phenotype</name>
                <description>Cells and tissues are exposed to stress from numerous sources. Senescence is a protective mechanism that prevents malignant tissue changes and constitutes a fundamental mechanism of aging. It can be accompanied by a senescence associated secretory phenotype (SASP) that causes chronic inflammation. We present a Boolean network model-based gene regulatory network of the SASP, incorporating published gene interaction data. The simulation results describe current biological knowledge. The model predicts different in-silico knockouts that prevent key SASP-mediators, IL-6 and IL-8, from getting activated upon DNA damage. The NF-&#954;B Essential Modulator (NEMO) was the most promising in-silico knockout candidate and we were able to show its importance in the inhibition of IL-6 and IL-8 following DNA-damage in murine dermal fibroblasts in-vitro. We strengthen the speculated regulator function of the NF-&#954;B signaling pathway in the onset and maintenance of the SASP using in-silico and in-vitro approaches. We were able to mechanistically show, that DNA damage mediated SASP triggering of IL-6 and IL-8 is mainly relayed through NF-&#954;B, giving access to possible therapy targets for SASP-accompanied diseases.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#11863:1/senescence-associated-secretory-phenotype</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2017-12-11"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2018-04-03 09:33:27"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2017-12-11 10:41:38</field>
                    <field name="model_score">33.6512</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2136">
                <name>Cardiac development</name>
                <description>Two types of distinct cardiac progenitor cell populations can be identified during early heart development: the first heart field (FHF) and second heart field (SHF) lineage that later form the mature heart. They can be characterized by differential expression of transcription and signaling factors. These regulatory factors influence each other forming a gene regulatory network. Here, we present a core gene regulatory network for early cardiac development based on published temporal and spatial expression data of genes and their interactions. This gene regulatory network was implemented in a Boolean computational model. Simulations reveal stable states within the network model, which correspond to the regulatory states of the FHF and the SHF lineages. Furthermore, we are able to reproduce the expected temporal expression patterns of early cardiac factors mimicking developmental progression. Additionally, simulations of knock-down experiments within our model resemble published phenotypes of mutant mice. Consequently, this gene regulatory network retraces the early steps and requirements of cardiogenic mesoderm determination in a way appropriate to enhance the understanding of heart development.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2136:1/cardiac-development</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-06-06"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-07-19 14:23:23"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-06-06 05:52:12</field>
                    <field name="model_score">12.4211</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2394">
                <name>B cell differentiation</name>
                <description>A dynamic model for the regulatory network that controls terminal B cell differentiation</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2394:1/b-cell-differentiation</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2014-05-12"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-27 22:29:04"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2014-05-12 11:52:07</field>
                    <field name="model_score">27.397800000000004</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2396">
                <name>Mammalian Cell Cycle 2006</name>
                <description>Motivation: To understand the behaviour of complex biological regulatory networks, a proper integration of molecular data into a full-fledge formal dynamical model is ultimately required. As most available data on regulatory interactions are qualitative, logical modelling offers an interesting framework to delineate the main dynamical properties of the underlying networks. Results: Transposing a generic model of the core network controlling the mammalian cell cycle into the logical framework, we compare different strategies to explore its dynamical properties. In particular, we assess the respective advantages and limits of synchronous versus asynchronous updating assumptions to delineate the asymptotical behaviour of regulatory networks. Furthermore, we propose several intermediate strategies to optimize the computation of asymptotical properties depending on available knowledge. Availability: The mammalian cell cycle model is available in a dedicated XML format (GINML) on our website, along with our logical simulation software GINsim (http://gin.univ-mrs.fr/GINsim). Higher resolution state transitions graphs are also found on this web site (Model Repository page).</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2396:1/mammalian-cell-cycle-2006</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2014-05-13"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-07-19 12:04:56"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2014-05-13 18:38:11</field>
                    <field name="model_score">132.8041</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="4705">
                <name>Septation Initiation Network</name>
                <description>The Septation Initiation Network (SIN) controls cytokinesis in fission yeast. This model uses CDK activity levels as control nodes to simutate SIN related events throughout different stages of the cell cycle. This model was optimized using single knock-out experiments and has made in silico predictions that have been validated in vivo, offering new insights into regulation of the SIN. </description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#4705:1/septation-initiation-network</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2016-07-21"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-02-06 11:12:49"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2016-07-21 18:05:02</field>
                    <field name="model_score">29.900000000000002</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="4706">
                <name>Predicting Variabilities in Cardiac Gene</name>
                <description>Gene interactions in cells can be represented by gene regulatory networks. A Boolean network models gene interactions according to rules where gene expression is represented by binary values (on / off or {1, 0}). In reality, however, the gene&#8217;s state can have multiple values due to biological properties. Furthermore, the noisy nature of the experimental design results in uncertainty about a state of the gene. Here we present a new Boolean network paradigm to allow intermediate values on the interval [0, 1]. As in the Boolean network, fixed points or attractors of such a model correspond to biological phenotypes or states. We use our new extension of the Boolean network paradigm to model gene expression in first and second heart field lineages which are cardiac progenitor cell populations involved in early vertebrate heart development. By this we are able to predict additional biological phenotypes that the Boolean model alone is not able to identify without utilizing additional biological knowledge. The additional phenotypes predicted by the model were confirmed by published biological experiments. Furthermore, the new method predicts gene expression propensities for modelled but yet to be analyzed genes.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#4706:1/predicting-variabilities-in-cardiac-gene</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2016-07-21"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-02-13 13:39:00"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2016-07-21 21:32:19</field>
                    <field name="model_score">19.400000000000002</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="5731">
                <name>Metabolic Interactions in the Gut Microbiome</name>
                <description>We present a novel methodology to construct a Boolean dynamic model from time series metagenomic information and integrate this modeling with genome-scale metabolic network reconstructions to identify metabolic underpinnings for microbial interactions. We apply this in the context of a critical health issue: clindamycin antibiotic treatment and opportunistic Clostridium difficile infection. Our model recapitulates known dynamics of clindamycin antibiotic treatment and C. difficile infection and predicts therapeutic probiotic interventions to suppress C. difficile infection. Genome-scale metabolic network reconstructions reveal metabolic differences between community members and are used to explore the role of metabolism in the observed microbial interactions. In vitro experimental data validate a key result of our computational model, that B. intestinihominis can in fact slow C. difficile growth.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#5731:1/metabolic-interactions-in-the-gut-microbiome</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2016-12-23"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-04-10 16:11:19"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2016-12-23 21:22:20</field>
                    <field name="model_score">10.3458</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2404">
                <name>Budding Yeast Cell Cycle</name>
                <description>It has been suggested that irreducible sets of states in Probabilistic Boolean Networks correspond to cellular phenotype. In this study, we identify such sets of states for each phase of the budding yeast cell cycle. We find that these &#8220;ergodic sets&#8221; underly the cyclin activity levels during each phase of the cell cycle. Our results compare to the observations made in several laboratory experiments as well as the results of differential equation models. Dynamical studies of this model: (i) indicate that under stochastic external signals the continuous oscillating waves of cyclin activity and the opposing waves of CKIs emerge from the logic of a Boolean-based regulatory network without the need for specific biochemical/kinetic parameters; (ii) suggest that the yeast cell cycle network is robust to the varying behavior of cell size (e.g., cell division under nitrogen deprived conditions); (iii) suggest the irreversibility of the Start signal is a function of logic of the G1 regulon, and changing the structure of the regulatory network can render start reversible.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2404:1/budding-yeast-cell-cycle</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2014-05-30"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2014-05-30 08:49:37</field>
                    <field name="model_score">8.841000000000001</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2407">
                <name>T-LGL Survival Network 2011</name>
                <description>The blood cancer T cell large granular lymphocyte (T-LGL) leukemia is a chronic disease characterized by a clonal proliferation of cytotoxic T cells. As no curative therapy is yet known for this disease, identification of potential therapeutic targets is of immense importance. In this paper, we perform a comprehensive dynamical and structural analysis of a network model of this disease. By employing a network reduction technique, we identify the stationary states (fixed points) of the system, representing normal and diseased (T-LGL) behavior, and analyze their precursor states (basins of attraction) using an asynchronous Boolean dynamic framework. This analysis identifies the T-LGL states of 54 components of the network, out of which 36 (67%) are corroborated by previous experimental evidence and the rest are novel predictions. We further test and validate one of these newly identified states experimentally. Specifically, we verify the prediction that the node SMAD is over-active in leukemic T-LGL by demonstrating the predominant phosphorylation of the SMAD family members Smad2 and Smad3. Our systematic perturbation analysis using dynamical and structural methods leads to the identification of 19 potential therapeutic targets, 68% of which are corroborated by experimental evidence. The novel therapeutic targets provide valuable guidance for wet-bench experiments. In addition, we successfully identify two new candidates for engineering long-lived T cells necessary for the delivery of virus and cancer vaccines. Overall, this study provides a bird's-eye-view of the avenues available for identification of therapeutic targets for similar diseases through perturbation of the underlying signal transduction network.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2407:1/tlgl-survival-network-2011</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2014-06-02"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2018-06-05 17:06:09"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2014-06-02 15:59:23</field>
                    <field name="model_score">29.950400000000002</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2663">
                <name>Wg Pathway of Drosophila Signalling Pathways</name>
                <description>A limited number of signalling pathways are involved in the specification of cell fate during the development of all animals. Several of these pathways were originally identified in Drosophila. To clarify their roles, and possible cross-talk, we have built a logical model for the nine key signalling pathways recurrently used in metazoan development. In each case, we considered the associated ligands, receptors, signal transducers, modulators, and transcription factors reported in the literature. Implemented using the logical modelling software GINsim, the resulting models qualitatively recapitulate the main characteristics of each pathway, in wild type as well as in various mutant situations (e.g. loss-of-function or gain-of-function). These models constitute pluggable modules that can be used to assemble comprehensive models of complex developmental processes. Moreover, these models of Drosophila pathways could serve as scaffolds for more complicated models of orthologous mammalian pathways. Comprehensive model annotations and GINsim files are provided for each of the nine considered pathways.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2663:1/wg-pathway-of-drosophila-signalling-pathways</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2015-01-22"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2015-01-22 11:06:24</field>
                    <field name="model_score">2.5</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2667">
                <name>VEGF Pathway of Drosophila Signaling Pathway</name>
                <description>A limited number of signalling pathways are involved in the specification of cell fate during the development of all animals. Several of these pathways were originally identified in Drosophila. To clarify their roles, and possible cross-talk, we have built a logical model for the nine key signalling pathways recurrently used in metazoan development. In each case, we considered the associated ligands, receptors, signal transducers, modulators, and transcription factors reported in the literature. Implemented using the logical modelling software GINsim, the resulting models qualitatively recapitulate the main characteristics of each pathway, in wild type as well as in various mutant situations (e.g. loss-of-function or gain-of-function). These models constitute pluggable modules that can be used to assemble comprehensive models of complex developmental processes. Moreover, these models of Drosophila pathways could serve as scaffolds for more complicated models of orthologous mammalian pathways. Comprehensive model annotations and GINsim files are provided for each of the nine considered pathways. (Fig3C from the paper)</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2667:1/vegf-pathway-of-drosophila-signaling-pathway</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2015-01-28"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2015-01-28 19:13:29</field>
                    <field name="model_score">2.1</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2668">
                <name>Toll Pathway of Drosophila Signaling Pathway</name>
                <description>A limited number of signalling pathways are involved in the specification of cell fate during the development of all animals. Several of these pathways were originally identified in Drosophila. To clarify their roles, and possible cross-talk, we have built a logical model for the nine key signalling pathways recurrently used in metazoan development. In each case, we considered the associated ligands, receptors, signal transducers, modulators, and transcription factors reported in the literature. Implemented using the logical modelling software GINsim, the resulting models qualitatively recapitulate the main characteristics of each pathway, in wild type as well as in various mutant situations (e.g. loss-of-function or gain-of-function). These models constitute pluggable modules that can be used to assemble comprehensive models of complex developmental processes. Moreover, these models of Drosophila pathways could serve as scaffolds for more complicated models of orthologous mammalian pathways. Comprehensive model annotations and GINsim files are provided for each of the nine considered pathways.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2668:1/toll-pathway-of-drosophila-signaling-pathway</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2015-01-28"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2015-01-28 19:24:15</field>
                    <field name="model_score">2.02</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2669">
                <name>Processing of Spz Network from the Drosophila Signaling Pathway</name>
                <description>A limited number of signalling pathways are involved in the specification of cell fate during the development of all animals. Several of these pathways were originally identified in Drosophila. To clarify their roles, and possible cross-talk, we have built a logical model for the nine key signalling pathways recurrently used in metazoan development. In each case, we considered the associated ligands, receptors, signal transducers, modulators, and transcription factors reported in the literature. Implemented using the logical modelling software GINsim, the resulting models qualitatively recapitulate the main characteristics of each pathway, in wild type as well as in various mutant situations (e.g. loss-of-function or gain-of-function). These models constitute pluggable modules that can be used to assemble comprehensive models of complex developmental processes. Moreover, these models of Drosophila pathways could serve as scaffolds for more complicated models of orthologous mammalian pathways. Comprehensive model annotations and GINsim files are provided for each of the nine considered pathways.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2669:1/processing-of-spz-network-from-the-drosophila-signaling-pathway</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2015-01-29"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2015-01-29 11:48:07</field>
                    <field name="model_score">4.0</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="8558">
                <name>Inflammatory Bowel Disease (IBD) Model</name>
                <description>A Systems Pharmacology model for Inflammatory Bowel Disease</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#8558:1/inflammatory-bowel-disease-(ibd)-model</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2017-09-18"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2018-04-05 09:49:13"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2017-09-18 11:00:21</field>
                    <field name="model_score">4.5101</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="8048">
                <name>Treatment of Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer</name>
                <description>Background:  Prostate cancer is one of the most prevalent cancers in males in the United States and amongst the leading causes of cancer related deaths. A particularly virulent form of this disease is castration-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC), where patients no longer respond to medical or surgical castration. CRPC is a complex, multifaceted and heterogeneous malady with limited standard treatment options.Results:  The growth and progression of prostate cancer is a complicated process that involves multiple pathways. The signaling network comprising the integral constituents of the signature pathways involved in the development and progression of prostate cancer is modeled as a combinatorial circuit. The failures in the gene regulatory network that lead to cancer are abstracted as faults in the equivalent circuit and the Boolean circuit model is then used to design therapies tailored to counteract the effect of each molecular abnormality and to propose potentially efficacious combinatorial therapy regimens. Furthermore, stochastic computational modeling is utilized to identify potentially vulnerable components in the network that may serve as viable candidates for drug development. Conclusion:  The results presented herein can aid in the design of scientifically well-grounded targeted therapies that can be employed for the treatment of prostate cancer patients.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#8048:1/treatment-of-castrationresistant-prostate-cancer</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2017-05-31"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-07-18 13:54:04"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2017-05-31 11:51:08</field>
                    <field name="model_score">25.800900000000002</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2161">
                <name>Guard Cell Abscisic Acid Signaling</name>
                <description>Plants both lose water and take in carbon dioxide through microscopic stomatal pores, each of which is regulated by a surrounding pair of guard cells. During drought, the plant hormone abscisic acid (ABA) inhibits stomatal opening and promotes stomatal closure, thereby promoting water conservation. Dozens of cellular components have been identified to function in ABA regulation of guard cell volume and thus of stomatal aperture, but a dynamic description is still not available for this complex process. Here we synthesize experimental results into a consistent guard cell signal transduction network for ABA-induced stomatal closure, and develop a dynamic model of this process. Our model captures the regulation of more than 40 identified network components, and accords well with previous experimental results at both the pathway and whole-cell physiological level. By simulating gene disruptions and pharmacological interventions we find that the network is robust against a significant fraction of possible perturbations. Our analysis reveals the novel predictions that the disruption of membrane depolarizability, anion efflux, actin cytoskeleton reorganization, cytosolic pH increase, the phosphatidic acid pathway, or K(+) efflux through slowly activating K(+) channels at the plasma membrane lead to the strongest reduction in ABA responsiveness. Initial experimental analysis assessing ABA-induced stomatal closure in the presence of cytosolic pH clamp imposed by the weak acid butyrate is consistent with model prediction. Simulations of stomatal response as derived from our model provide an efficient tool for the identification of candidate manipulations that have the best chance of conferring increased drought stress tolerance and for the prioritization of future wet bench analyses. Our method can be readily applied to other biological signaling networks to identify key regulatory components in systems where quantitative information is limited.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2161:1/guard-cell-abscisic-acid-signaling</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-06-20"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-07-19 12:01:07"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-06-20 03:09:04</field>
                    <field name="model_score">106.2161</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2423">
                <name>Budding Yeast Cell Cycle 2009</name>
                <description>Abstract The budding yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae is a model organism that is commonly used to investigate control of the eukaryotic cell cycle. Moreover, because of the extensive experimental data on wild type and mutant phenotypes, it is also particularly suitable for mathematical modelling and analysis. Here, I present a new Boolean model of the budding yeast cell cycle. This model is consistent with a wide range of wild type and mutant phenotypes and shows remarkable robustness against perturbations, both to reaction times and the states of component genes/proteins. Because of its simple logical nature, the model is suitable for sub-network analysis, which can be used to identify a four node core regulatory circuit underlying cell cycle regulation. Sub-network analysis can also be used to identify key sub-dynamics that are essential for viable cell cycle control, as well as identifying the sub-dynamics that are most variable between different mutants.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2423:1/budding-yeast-cell-cycle-2009</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2014-06-18"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-03-29 23:24:54"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2014-06-18 11:38:15</field>
                    <field name="model_score">28.0736</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2681">
                <name>Cell Cycle Transcription by Coupled CDK and Network Oscillators</name>
                <description>A significant fraction of the Saccharomyces cerevisiae genome is transcribed periodically during the cell division cycle, indicating that properly timed gene expression is important for regulating cell-cycle events. Genomic analyses of the localization and expression dynamics of transcription factors suggest that a network of sequentially expressed transcription factors could control the temporal programme of transcription during the cell cycle3. However, directed studies interrogating small numbers of genes indicate that their periodic transcription is governed by the activity of cyclin-dependent kinases (CDKs)4. To determine the extent to which the global cell-cycle transcription programme is controlled by cyclin&#8211;CDK complexes, we examined genome-wide transcription dynamics in budding yeast mutant cells that do not express S-phase and mitotic cyclins. Here we show that a significant fraction of periodic genes are aberrantly expressed in the cyclin mutant. Although cells lacking cyclins are blocked at the G1/S border, nearly 70% of periodic genes continued to be expressed periodically and on schedule. Our findings reveal that although CDKs have a function in the regulation of cell-cycle transcription, they are not solely responsible for establishing the global periodic transcription programme. We propose that periodic transcription is an emergent property of a transcription factor network that can function as a cell-cycle oscillator independently of, and in tandem with, the CDK oscillator.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2681:1/cell-cycle-transcription-by-coupled-cdk-and-network-oscillators</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2015-02-05"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2015-02-05 09:45:30</field>
                    <field name="model_score">57.322399999999995</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2171">
                <name>T Cell Receptor Signaling</name>
                <description>Cellular decisions are determined by complex molecular interaction networks. Large-scale signaling networks are currently being reconstructed, but the kinetic parameters and quantitative data that would allow for dynamic modeling are still scarce. Therefore, computational studies based upon the structure of these networks are of great interest. Here, a methodology relying on a logical formalism is applied to the functional analysis of the complex signaling network governing the activation of T cells via the T cell receptor, the CD4/CD8 co-receptors, and the accessory signaling receptor CD28. Our large-scale Boolean model, which comprises 94 nodes and 123 interactions and is based upon well-established qualitative knowledge from primary T cells, reveals important structural features (e.g., feedback loops and network-wide dependencies) and recapitulates the global behavior of this network for an array of published data on T cell activation in wild-type and knock-out conditions. More importantly, the model predicted unexpected signaling events after antibody-mediated perturbation of CD28 and after genetic knockout of the kinase Fyn that were subsequently experimentally validated. Finally, we show that the logical model reveals key elements and potential failure modes in network functioning and provides candidates for missing links. In summary, our large-scale logical model for T cell activation proved to be a promising in silico tool, and it inspires immunologists to ask new questions. We think that it holds valuable potential in foreseeing the effects of drugs and network modifications.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2171:1/t-cell-receptor-signaling</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-06-24"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2019-08-09 15:06:11"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-06-24 02:02:56</field>
                    <field name="model_score">92.8552</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2172">
                <name>Cholesterol Regulatory Pathway</name>
                <description>BACKGROUND: Qualitative dynamics of small gene regulatory networks have been studied in quite some details both with synchronous and asynchronous analysis. However, both methods have their drawbacks: synchronous analysis leads to spurious attractors and asynchronous analysis lacks computational efficiency, which is a problem to simulate large networks. We addressed this question through the analysis of a major biosynthesis pathway. Indeed the cholesterol synthesis pathway plays a pivotal role in dislypidemia and, ultimately, in cancer through intermediates such as mevalonate, farnesyl pyrophosphate and geranyl geranyl pyrophosphate, but no dynamic model of this pathway has been proposed until now. RESULTS: We set up a computational framework to dynamically analyze large biological networks. This framework associates a classical and computationally efficient synchronous Boolean analysis with a newly introduced method based on Markov chains, which identifies spurious cycles among the results of the synchronous simulation. Based on this method, we present here the results of the analysis of the cholesterol biosynthesis pathway and its physiological regulation by the Sterol Response Element Binding Proteins (SREBPs), as well as the modeling of the action of statins, inhibitor drugs, on this pathway. The in silico experiments show the blockade of the cholesterol endogenous synthesis by statins and its regulation by SREPBs, in full agreement with the known biochemical features of the pathway. CONCLUSION: We believe that the method described here to identify spurious cycles opens new routes to compute large and biologically relevant models, thanks to the computational efficiency of synchronous simulation. Furthermore, to the best of our knowledge, we present here the first dynamic systems biology model of the human cholesterol pathway and several of its key regulatory control elements, hoping it would provide a good basis to perform in silico experiments and confront the resulting properties with published and experimental data. The model of the cholesterol pathway and its regulation, along with Boolean formulae used for simulation are available on our web site http://Bioinformaticsu613.free.fr. Graphical results of the simulation are also shown online. The SBML model is available in the BioModels database http://www.ebi.ac.uk/biomodels/ with submission ID: MODEL0568648427.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2172:1/cholesterol-regulatory-pathway</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-06-24"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-23 07:51:39"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-06-24 13:35:08</field>
                    <field name="model_score">8.2</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2176">
                <name>T-LGL Survival Network 2008</name>
                <description>T cell large granular lymphocyte (T-LGL) leukemia features a clonal expansion of antigen-primed, competent, cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTL). To systematically understand signaling components that determine the survival of CTL in T-LGL leukemia, we constructed a T-LGL survival signaling network by integrating the signaling pathways involved in normal CTL activation and the known deregulations of survival signaling in leukemic T-LGL. This network was subsequently translated into a predictive, discrete, dynamic model. Our model suggests that the persistence of IL-15 and PDGF is sufficient to reproduce all known deregulations in leukemic T-LGL. This finding leads to the following predictions: (i) Inhibiting PDGF signaling induces apoptosis in leukemic T-LGL. (ii) Sphingosine kinase 1 and NF?B are essential for the long-term survival of CTL in T-LGL leukemia. (iii) NF?B functions downstream of PI3K and prevents apoptosis through maintaining the expression of myeloid cell leukemia sequence 1. (iv) T box expressed in T cells (T-bet) should be constitutively activated concurrently with NF?B activation to reproduce the leukemic T-LGL phenotype. We validated these predictions experimentally. Our study provides a model describing the signaling network involved in maintaining the long-term survival of competent CTL in humans. The model will be useful in identifying potential therapeutic targets for T-LGL leukemia and generating long-term competent CTL necessary for tumor and cancer vaccine development.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2176:1/tlgl-survival-network-2008</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-06-26"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-05-15 16:34:31"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-06-26 11:38:44</field>
                    <field name="model_score">66.9082</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2691">
                <name>T-Cell Signaling 2006</name>
                <description>Background Structural analysis of cellular interaction networks contributes to a deeper understanding of network-wide interdependencies, causal relationships, and basic functional capabilities. While the structural analysis of metabolic networks is a well-established field, similar methodologies have been scarcely developed and applied to signaling and regulatory networks.  Results We propose formalisms and methods, relying on adapted and partially newly introduced approaches, which facilitate a structural analysis of signaling and regulatory networks with focus on functional aspects. We use two different formalisms to represent and analyze interaction networks: interaction graphs and (logical) interaction hypergraphs. We show that, in interaction graphs, the determination of feedback cycles and of all the signaling paths between any pair of species is equivalent to the computation of elementary modes known from metabolic networks. Knowledge on the set of signaling paths and feedback loops facilitates the computation of intervention strategies and the classification of compounds into activators, inhibitors, ambivalent factors, and non-affecting factors with respect to a certain species. In some cases, qualitative effects induced by perturbations can be unambiguously predicted from the network scheme. Interaction graphs however, are not able to capture AND relationships which do frequently occur in interaction networks. The consequent logical concatenation of all the arcs pointing into a species leads to Boolean networks. For a Boolean representation of cellular interaction networks we propose a formalism based on logical (or signed) interaction hypergraphs, which facilitates in particular a logical steady state analysis (LSSA). LSSA enables studies on the logical processing of signals and the identification of optimal intervention points (targets) in cellular networks. LSSA also reveals network regions whose parametrization and initial states are crucial for the dynamic behavior.  We have implemented these methods in our software tool CellNetAnalyzer (successor of FluxAnalyzer) and illustrate their applicability using a logical model of T-Cell receptor signaling providing non-intuitive results regarding feedback loops, essential elements, and (logical) signal processing upon different stimuli.  Conclusion The methods and formalisms we propose herein are another step towards the comprehensive functional analysis of cellular interaction networks. Their potential, shown on a realistic T-cell signaling model, makes them a promising tool.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2691:1/tcell-signaling-2006</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2015-02-09"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2015-02-09 12:00:08</field>
                    <field name="model_score">98.9314</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2697">
                <name>BT474 Breast Cell Line Long-term ErbB Network</name>
                <description>Background Despite promising progress in targeted breast cancer therapy, drug resistance remains challenging. The monoclonal antibody drugs trastuzumab and pertuzumab as well as the small molecule inhibitor erlotinib were designed to prevent ErbB-2 and ErbB-1 receptor induced deregulated protein signalling, contributing to tumour progression. The oncogenic potential of ErbB receptors unfolds in case of overexpression or mutations. Dimerisation with other receptors allows to bypass pathway blockades. Our intention is to reconstruct the ErbB network to reveal resistance mechanisms. We used longitudinal proteomic data of ErbB receptors and downstream targets in the ErbB-2 amplified breast cancer cell lines BT474, SKBR3 and HCC1954 treated with erlotinib, trastuzumab or pertuzumab, alone or combined, up to 60 minutes and 30 hours, respectively. In a Boolean modelling approach, signalling networks were reconstructed based on these data in a cell line and time course specific manner, including prior literature knowledge. Finally, we simulated network response to inhibitor combinations to detect signalling nodes reflecting growth inhibition.  Results The networks pointed to cell line specific activation patterns of the MAPK and PI3K pathway. In BT474, the PI3K signal route was favoured, while in SKBR3, novel edges highlighted MAPK signalling. In HCC1954, the inferred edges stimulated both pathways. For example, we uncovered feedback loops amplifying PI3K signalling, in line with the known trastuzumab resistance of this cell line. In the perturbation simulations on the short-term networks, we analysed ERK1/2, AKT and p70S6K. The results indicated a pathway specific drug response, driven by the type of growth factor stimulus. HCC1954 revealed an edgetic type of PIK3CA-mutation, contributing to trastuzumab inefficacy. Drug impact on the AKT and ERK1/2 signalling axes is mirrored by effects on RB and RPS6, relating to phenotypic events like cell growth or proliferation. Therefore, we additionally analysed RB and RPS6 in the long-term networks.  Conclusions We derived protein interaction models for three breast cancer cell lines. Changes compared to the common reference network hint towards individual characteristics and potential drug resistance mechanisms. Simulation of perturbations were consistent with the experimental data, confirming our combined reverse and forward engineering approach as valuable for drug discovery and personalised medicine.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2697:1/bt474-breast-cell-line-longterm-erbb-network</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2015-02-17"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2015-02-17 13:38:17</field>
                    <field name="model_score">4.2</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2698">
                <name>HCC1954 Breast Cell Line Long-term ErbB Network</name>
                <description>Background Despite promising progress in targeted breast cancer therapy, drug resistance remains challenging. The monoclonal antibody drugs trastuzumab and pertuzumab as well as the small molecule inhibitor erlotinib were designed to prevent ErbB-2 and ErbB-1 receptor induced deregulated protein signalling, contributing to tumour progression. The oncogenic potential of ErbB receptors unfolds in case of overexpression or mutations. Dimerisation with other receptors allows to bypass pathway blockades. Our intention is to reconstruct the ErbB network to reveal resistance mechanisms. We used longitudinal proteomic data of ErbB receptors and downstream targets in the ErbB-2 amplified breast cancer cell lines BT474, SKBR3 and HCC1954 treated with erlotinib, trastuzumab or pertuzumab, alone or combined, up to 60 minutes and 30 hours, respectively. In a Boolean modelling approach, signalling networks were reconstructed based on these data in a cell line and time course specific manner, including prior literature knowledge. Finally, we simulated network response to inhibitor combinations to detect signalling nodes reflecting growth inhibition.  Results The networks pointed to cell line specific activation patterns of the MAPK and PI3K pathway. In BT474, the PI3K signal route was favoured, while in SKBR3, novel edges highlighted MAPK signalling. In HCC1954, the inferred edges stimulated both pathways. For example, we uncovered feedback loops amplifying PI3K signalling, in line with the known trastuzumab resistance of this cell line. In the perturbation simulations on the short-term networks, we analysed ERK1/2, AKT and p70S6K. The results indicated a pathway specific drug response, driven by the type of growth factor stimulus. HCC1954 revealed an edgetic type of PIK3CA-mutation, contributing to trastuzumab inefficacy. Drug impact on the AKT and ERK1/2 signalling axes is mirrored by effects on RB and RPS6, relating to phenotypic events like cell growth or proliferation. Therefore, we additionally analysed RB and RPS6 in the long-term networks.  Conclusions We derived protein interaction models for three breast cancer cell lines. Changes compared to the common reference network hint towards individual characteristics and potential drug resistance mechanisms. Simulation of perturbations were consistent with the experimental data, confirming our combined reverse and forward engineering approach as valuable for drug discovery and personalised medicine.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2698:1/hcc1954-breast-cell-line-longterm-erbb-network</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2015-02-17"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2015-02-17 14:00:12</field>
                    <field name="model_score">3.5</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2699">
                <name>BT474 Breast Cell Line Short-term ErbB Network</name>
                <description>Background Despite promising progress in targeted breast cancer therapy, drug resistance remains challenging. The monoclonal antibody drugs trastuzumab and pertuzumab as well as the small molecule inhibitor erlotinib were designed to prevent ErbB-2 and ErbB-1 receptor induced deregulated protein signalling, contributing to tumour progression. The oncogenic potential of ErbB receptors unfolds in case of overexpression or mutations. Dimerisation with other receptors allows to bypass pathway blockades. Our intention is to reconstruct the ErbB network to reveal resistance mechanisms. We used longitudinal proteomic data of ErbB receptors and downstream targets in the ErbB-2 amplified breast cancer cell lines BT474, SKBR3 and HCC1954 treated with erlotinib, trastuzumab or pertuzumab, alone or combined, up to 60 minutes and 30 hours, respectively. In a Boolean modelling approach, signalling networks were reconstructed based on these data in a cell line and time course specific manner, including prior literature knowledge. Finally, we simulated network response to inhibitor combinations to detect signalling nodes reflecting growth inhibition.  Results The networks pointed to cell line specific activation patterns of the MAPK and PI3K pathway. In BT474, the PI3K signal route was favoured, while in SKBR3, novel edges highlighted MAPK signalling. In HCC1954, the inferred edges stimulated both pathways. For example, we uncovered feedback loops amplifying PI3K signalling, in line with the known trastuzumab resistance of this cell line. In the perturbation simulations on the short-term networks, we analysed ERK1/2, AKT and p70S6K. The results indicated a pathway specific drug response, driven by the type of growth factor stimulus. HCC1954 revealed an edgetic type of PIK3CA-mutation, contributing to trastuzumab inefficacy. Drug impact on the AKT and ERK1/2 signalling axes is mirrored by effects on RB and RPS6, relating to phenotypic events like cell growth or proliferation. Therefore, we additionally analysed RB and RPS6 in the long-term networks.  Conclusions We derived protein interaction models for three breast cancer cell lines. Changes compared to the common reference network hint towards individual characteristics and potential drug resistance mechanisms. Simulation of perturbations were consistent with the experimental data, confirming our combined reverse and forward engineering approach as valuable for drug discovery and personalised medicine.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2699:1/bt474-breast-cell-line-shortterm-erbb-network</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2015-02-17"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2015-02-17 15:11:45</field>
                    <field name="model_score">4.300000000000001</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2700">
                <name>HCC1954 Breast Cell Line Short-term ErbB Network</name>
                <description>Background Despite promising progress in targeted breast cancer therapy, drug resistance remains challenging. The monoclonal antibody drugs trastuzumab and pertuzumab as well as the small molecule inhibitor erlotinib were designed to prevent ErbB-2 and ErbB-1 receptor induced deregulated protein signalling, contributing to tumour progression. The oncogenic potential of ErbB receptors unfolds in case of overexpression or mutations. Dimerisation with other receptors allows to bypass pathway blockades. Our intention is to reconstruct the ErbB network to reveal resistance mechanisms. We used longitudinal proteomic data of ErbB receptors and downstream targets in the ErbB-2 amplified breast cancer cell lines BT474, SKBR3 and HCC1954 treated with erlotinib, trastuzumab or pertuzumab, alone or combined, up to 60 minutes and 30 hours, respectively. In a Boolean modelling approach, signalling networks were reconstructed based on these data in a cell line and time course specific manner, including prior literature knowledge. Finally, we simulated network response to inhibitor combinations to detect signalling nodes reflecting growth inhibition.  Results The networks pointed to cell line specific activation patterns of the MAPK and PI3K pathway. In BT474, the PI3K signal route was favoured, while in SKBR3, novel edges highlighted MAPK signalling. In HCC1954, the inferred edges stimulated both pathways. For example, we uncovered feedback loops amplifying PI3K signalling, in line with the known trastuzumab resistance of this cell line. In the perturbation simulations on the short-term networks, we analysed ERK1/2, AKT and p70S6K. The results indicated a pathway specific drug response, driven by the type of growth factor stimulus. HCC1954 revealed an edgetic type of PIK3CA-mutation, contributing to trastuzumab inefficacy. Drug impact on the AKT and ERK1/2 signalling axes is mirrored by effects on RB and RPS6, relating to phenotypic events like cell growth or proliferation. Therefore, we additionally analysed RB and RPS6 in the long-term networks.  Conclusions We derived protein interaction models for three breast cancer cell lines. Changes compared to the common reference network hint towards individual characteristics and potential drug resistance mechanisms. Simulation of perturbations were consistent with the experimental data, confirming our combined reverse and forward engineering approach as valuable for drug discovery and personalised medicine.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2700:1/hcc1954-breast-cell-line-shortterm-erbb-network</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2015-02-17"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2015-02-17 15:30:41</field>
                    <field name="model_score">3.9000000000000004</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2701">
                <name>SKBR3 Breast Cell Line Short-term ErbB Network</name>
                <description>Background Despite promising progress in targeted breast cancer therapy, drug resistance remains challenging. The monoclonal antibody drugs trastuzumab and pertuzumab as well as the small molecule inhibitor erlotinib were designed to prevent ErbB-2 and ErbB-1 receptor induced deregulated protein signalling, contributing to tumour progression. The oncogenic potential of ErbB receptors unfolds in case of overexpression or mutations. Dimerisation with other receptors allows to bypass pathway blockades. Our intention is to reconstruct the ErbB network to reveal resistance mechanisms. We used longitudinal proteomic data of ErbB receptors and downstream targets in the ErbB-2 amplified breast cancer cell lines BT474, SKBR3 and HCC1954 treated with erlotinib, trastuzumab or pertuzumab, alone or combined, up to 60 minutes and 30 hours, respectively. In a Boolean modelling approach, signalling networks were reconstructed based on these data in a cell line and time course specific manner, including prior literature knowledge. Finally, we simulated network response to inhibitor combinations to detect signalling nodes reflecting growth inhibition.  Results The networks pointed to cell line specific activation patterns of the MAPK and PI3K pathway. In BT474, the PI3K signal route was favoured, while in SKBR3, novel edges highlighted MAPK signalling. In HCC1954, the inferred edges stimulated both pathways. For example, we uncovered feedback loops amplifying PI3K signalling, in line with the known trastuzumab resistance of this cell line. In the perturbation simulations on the short-term networks, we analysed ERK1/2, AKT and p70S6K. The results indicated a pathway specific drug response, driven by the type of growth factor stimulus. HCC1954 revealed an edgetic type of PIK3CA-mutation, contributing to trastuzumab inefficacy. Drug impact on the AKT and ERK1/2 signalling axes is mirrored by effects on RB and RPS6, relating to phenotypic events like cell growth or proliferation. Therefore, we additionally analysed RB and RPS6 in the long-term networks.  Conclusions We derived protein interaction models for three breast cancer cell lines. Changes compared to the common reference network hint towards individual characteristics and potential drug resistance mechanisms. Simulation of perturbations were consistent with the experimental data, confirming our combined reverse and forward engineering approach as valuable for drug discovery and personalised medicine.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2701:1/skbr3-breast-cell-line-shortterm-erbb-network</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2015-02-17"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2015-02-17 15:40:48</field>
                    <field name="model_score">3.8000000000000003</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2703">
                <name>SKBR3 Breast Cell Line Long-term ErbB Network</name>
                <description>Background Despite promising progress in targeted breast cancer therapy, drug resistance remains challenging. The monoclonal antibody drugs trastuzumab and pertuzumab as well as the small molecule inhibitor erlotinib were designed to prevent ErbB-2 and ErbB-1 receptor induced deregulated protein signalling, contributing to tumour progression. The oncogenic potential of ErbB receptors unfolds in case of overexpression or mutations. Dimerisation with other receptors allows to bypass pathway blockades. Our intention is to reconstruct the ErbB network to reveal resistance mechanisms. We used longitudinal proteomic data of ErbB receptors and downstream targets in the ErbB-2 amplified breast cancer cell lines BT474, SKBR3 and HCC1954 treated with erlotinib, trastuzumab or pertuzumab, alone or combined, up to 60 minutes and 30 hours, respectively. In a Boolean modelling approach, signalling networks were reconstructed based on these data in a cell line and time course specific manner, including prior literature knowledge. Finally, we simulated network response to inhibitor combinations to detect signalling nodes reflecting growth inhibition.  Results The networks pointed to cell line specific activation patterns of the MAPK and PI3K pathway. In BT474, the PI3K signal route was favoured, while in SKBR3, novel edges highlighted MAPK signalling. In HCC1954, the inferred edges stimulated both pathways. For example, we uncovered feedback loops amplifying PI3K signalling, in line with the known trastuzumab resistance of this cell line. In the perturbation simulations on the short-term networks, we analysed ERK1/2, AKT and p70S6K. The results indicated a pathway specific drug response, driven by the type of growth factor stimulus. HCC1954 revealed an edgetic type of PIK3CA-mutation, contributing to trastuzumab inefficacy. Drug impact on the AKT and ERK1/2 signalling axes is mirrored by effects on RB and RPS6, relating to phenotypic events like cell growth or proliferation. Therefore, we additionally analysed RB and RPS6 in the long-term networks.  Conclusions We derived protein interaction models for three breast cancer cell lines. Changes compared to the common reference network hint towards individual characteristics and potential drug resistance mechanisms. Simulation of perturbations were consistent with the experimental data, confirming our combined reverse and forward engineering approach as valuable for drug discovery and personalised medicine.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2703:1/skbr3-breast-cell-line-longterm-erbb-network</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2015-02-18"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2015-02-18 15:17:04</field>
                    <field name="model_score">2.9</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="8080">
                <name>Lymphopoiesis Regulatory Network</name>
                <description>Due to the large number of diseases associated to a malfunction of the hematopoietic system, there is an interest in knowing the molecular mechanisms controlling the differentiation of blood cell lineages. However, the structure and dynamical properties of the underlying regulatory network controlling this process is not well understood. This manuscript presents a regulatory network of 81 nodes, representing several types of molecules that regulate each other during the process of lymphopoiesis. The regulatory interactions were inferred mostly from published experimental data. However, 15 out of 159 regulatory interactions are predictions arising from the present study. The network is modelled as a continuous dynamical system, in the form of a set of differential equations. The dynamical behaviour of the model describes the differentiation process from the common lymphocyte precursor (CLP) to several mature B and T cell types; namely, plasma cell (PC), cytotoxic T lymphocyte (CTL), T helper 1 (Th1), Th2, Th17, and T regulatory (Treg) cells. The model qualitatively recapitulates key cellular differentiation events, being able to represent the directional and branched nature of lymphopoiesis, going from a multipotent progenitor to fully differentiated cell types.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#8080:1/lymphopoiesis-regulatory-network</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2017-06-07"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-07-25 20:40:27"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2017-06-07 15:25:38</field>
                    <field name="model_score">57.41160000000001</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="3481">
                <name>Influenza A Virus Replication Cycle</name>
                <description>The replication and life cycle of the influenza virus is governed by an intricate network of intracellular regulatory events during infection, including interactions with an even more complex system of biochemical interactions of the host cell. Computational modeling and systems biology have been successfully employed to further the understanding of various biological systems, however, computational studies of the complexity of intracellular interactions during influenza infection is lacking. In this work, we present the first large-scale dynamical model of the infection and replication cycle of influenza, as well as some of its interactions with the host's signaling machinery. Specifically, we focus on and visualize the dynamics of the internalization and endocytosis of the virus, replication and translation of its genomic components, as well as the assembly of progeny virions. Simulations and analyses of the models dynamics qualitatively reproduced numerous biological phenomena discovered in the laboratory. Finally, comparisons of the dynamics of existing and proposed drugs, our results suggest that a drug targeting PB1:PA would be more efficient than existing Amantadin/Rimantaine or Zanamivir/Oseltamivir.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#3481:1/influenza-a-virus-replication-cycle</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2012-03-19"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2012-03-19 00:16:44</field>
                    <field name="model_score">11.254999999999999</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2202">
                <name>Neurotransmitter Signaling Pathway</name>
                <description>Background  A Boolean network is a simple computational model that may provide insight into the overall behavior of genetic networks and is represented by variables with two possible states (on/off), of the individual nodes/genes of the network. In this study, a Boolean network model has been used to simulate a molecular pathway between two neurotransmitter receptor, dopamine and glutamate receptor, systems in order to understand the consequence of using logic gate rules between nodes, which have two possible states (active and inactive).  Results  The dynamical properties of this Boolean network model of the biochemical pathway shows that, the pathway is stable and that, deletion/knockout of certain biologically important nodes cause significant perturbation to this network. The analysis clearly shows that in addition to the expected components dopamine and dopamine receptor 2 (DRD2), Ca2+ ions play a critical role in maintaining stability of the pathway. Conclusion  So this method may be useful for the identification of potential genetic targets, whose loss of function in biochemical pathways may be responsible for disease onset. The molecular pathway considered in this study has been implicated with a complex disorder like schizophrenia, which has a complex multifactorial etiology.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2202:1/neurotransmitter-signaling-pathway</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-08-02"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2018-08-05 08:16:17"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-08-02 01:28:27</field>
                    <field name="model_score">9.122800000000002</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="5025">
                <name>CD4+ T Cell Differentiation and Plasticity</name>
                <description>CD4+ T cells orchestrate the adaptive immune response in vertebrates. While both experimental and modeling work has been conducted to understand the molecular genetic mechanisms involved in CD4+ T cell responses and fate attainment, the dynamic role of intrinsic (produced by CD4+ T lymphocytes) versus extrinsic (produced by other cells) components remains unclear, and the mechanistic and dynamic understanding of the plastic responses of these cells remains incomplete. In this work, we studied a regulatory network for the core transcription factors involved in CD4+ T cell-fate attainment. We first show that this core is not sufficient to recover common CD4+ T phenotypes. We thus postulate a minimal Boolean regulatory network model derived from a larger and more comprehensive network that is based on experimental data. The minimal network integrates transcriptional regulation, signaling pathways and the micro-environment. This network model recovers reported configurations of most of the characterized cell types (Th0, Th1, Th2, Th17, Tfh, Th9, iTreg, and Foxp3-independent T regulatory cells). This transcriptional-signaling regulatory network is robust and recovers mutant configurations that have been reported experimentally. Additionally, this model recovers many of the plasticity patterns documented for different T CD4+ cell types, as summarized in a cell-fate map. We tested the effects of various micro-environments and transient perturbations on such transitions among CD4+ T cell types. Interestingly, most cell-fate transitions were induced by transient activations, with the opposite behavior associated with transient inhibitions. Finally, we used a novel methodology was used to establish that T-bet, TGF-&#946; and suppressors of cytokine signaling proteins are keys to recovering observed CD4+ T cell plastic responses. In conclusion, the observed CD4+ T cell-types and transition patterns emerge from the feedback between the intrinsic or intracellular regulatory core and the micro-environment. We discuss the broader use of this approach for other plastic systems and possible therapeutic interventions.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#5025:1/cd4+-t-cell-differentiation-and-plasticity</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2016-10-28"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-02-25 18:06:48"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2016-10-28 14:33:21</field>
                    <field name="model_score">18.9614</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="3491">
                <name>TOL Regulatory Network</name>
                <description>The TOL system encoded by plasmid pWW0 of Pseudomonas putida mt-2 is able to sense a large number of both exogenous and endogenous signals as inputs for the genetic and metabolic circuit that determines the biodegradation of m-xylene. However, whether the enormous combinatorial space of inputs is translated into an equally variable response landscape or is processed into very few outcomes remains unclear. To address this question, we set out to define the number of states that can be obtained by a network of a given set of genes under the control of a specified regulatory circuit that is exposed to all possible combinations of inputs. To this end, the TOL network and its regulatory wiring were formalized as a synchronous logic Boolean circuit that had 10 signals (i.e. pathway substrates, temperature, sugars, amino acids, metabolic regimes and global regulators) as possible inputs. The analysis of the attractors of the circuit using a satisfiability (SAT) algorithm revealed that only eight transcriptional states are reached in response to the 1024 possible combinations of stimuli. The experimental validation resulted in a refinement of the model through the addition of a previously unknown interaction that controls the meta catabolic pathway. The full induction of the two xyl operons occurred with only 1.6% of the input combinations, which suggests that the architecture of the network allows the expression of the xyl genes only under a very narrow range of conditions. These data not only explain much of the unusual layout of the TOL circuit but also strengthen the view of the regulatory circuits of environmental bacteria as digital decision-making devices.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#3491:1/tol-regulatory-network</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-05-06"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-05-06 13:37:11</field>
                    <field name="model_score">6.9</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="3492">
                <name>Bordetella bronchiseptica</name>
                <description>Co-infections alter the host immune response but how the systemic and local processes at the site of infection interact is still unclear. The majority of studies on co-infections concentrate on one of the infecting species, an immune function or group of cells and often focus on the initial phase of the infection. Here, we used a combination of experiments and mathematical modelling to investigate the network of immune responses against single and co-infections with the respiratory bacterium Bordetella bronchiseptica and the gastrointestinal helminth Trichostrongylus retortaeformis. Our goal was to identify representative mediators and functions that could capture the essence of the host immune response as a whole, and to assess how their relative contribution dynamically changed over time and between single and co-infected individuals. Network-based discrete dynamic models of single infections were built using current knowledge of bacterial and helminth immunology; the two single infection models were combined into a co-infection model that was then verified by our empirical findings. Simulations showed that a T helper cell mediated antibody and neutrophil response led to phagocytosis and clearance of B. bronchiseptica from the lungs. This was consistent in single and co-infection with no significant delay induced by the helminth. In contrast, T. retortaeformis intensity decreased faster when co-infected with the bacterium. Simulations suggested that the robust recruitment of neutrophils in the co-infection, added to the activation of IgG and eosinophil driven reduction of larvae, which also played an important role in single infection, contributed to this fast clearance. Perturbation analysis of the models, through the knockout of individual nodes (immune cells), identified the cells critical to parasite persistence and clearance both in single and co-infections. Our integrated approach captured the within-host immuno-dynamics of bacteria-helminth infection and identified key components that can be crucial for explaining individual variability between single and co-infections in natural populations.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#3492:1/bordetella-bronchiseptica</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-06-16"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-06-16 07:46:41</field>
                    <field name="model_score">13.200000000000001</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="3493">
                <name>Trichostrongylus retortaeformis</name>
                <description>Co-infections alter the host immune response but how the systemic and local processes at the site of infection interact is still unclear. The majority of studies on co-infections concentrate on one of the infecting species, an immune function or group of cells and often focus on the initial phase of the infection. Here, we used a combination of experiments and mathematical modelling to investigate the network of immune responses against single and co-infections with the respiratory bacterium Bordetella bronchiseptica and the gastrointestinal helminth Trichostrongylus retortaeformis. Our goal was to identify representative mediators and functions that could capture the essence of the host immune response as a whole, and to assess how their relative contribution dynamically changed over time and between single and co-infected individuals. Network-based discrete dynamic models of single infections were built using current knowledge of bacterial and helminth immunology; the two single infection models were combined into a co-infection model that was then verified by our empirical findings. Simulations showed that a T helper cell mediated antibody and neutrophil response led to phagocytosis and clearance of B. bronchiseptica from the lungs. This was consistent in single and co-infection with no significant delay induced by the helminth. In contrast, T. retortaeformis intensity decreased faster when co-infected with the bacterium. Simulations suggested that the robust recruitment of neutrophils in the co-infection, added to the activation of IgG and eosinophil driven reduction of larvae, which also played an important role in single infection, contributed to this fast clearance. Perturbation analysis of the models, through the knockout of individual nodes (immune cells), identified the cells critical to parasite persistence and clearance both in single and co-infections. Our integrated approach captured the within-host immuno-dynamics of bacteria-helminth infection and identified key components that can be crucial for explaining individual variability between single and co-infections in natural populations.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#3493:1/trichostrongylus-retortaeformis</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-06-16"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-06-16 09:37:54</field>
                    <field name="model_score">9.8</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2214">
                <name>IL-1 Signaling</name>
                <description>The pro-inflammatory cytokines interleukin 1 (IL-1) and 6 (IL-6) are crucially involved in the regulation of a multitude of physiological processes, in particular coordinating the immune response upon bacterial infection and tissue injury. Both interleukins induce complex signalling cascades and trigger the production of mitogenic, pro-proliferative, anti-apoptotic, chemotactic, and pro-angiogenic factors thereby affecting the delicate balance between regenerationvs. invasive growth, tumourigenesis and metastasis. Moreover, several links to insulin resistance have been found within their associated signalling networks. Focusing on this from a systems biology perspective, we introduce comprehensive large-scale network models of IL-1 and IL-6 signalling which are based on a logical modelling approach and reflect the current biological knowledge. Theoretical network analysis enabled us to uncover general topological features and to make testable predictions on the stimulus-response behaviour of the networks. In this context, non-intuitive network-wide species dependencies as well as structures of regulatory feedback and feed-forward mechanisms could be characterised. By integrating high-throughput phosphoproteomic data from primary human hepatocytes we optimised the model structures to obtain models with high prediction accuracy for hepatocytes. Our model-based data analysis, for instance, suggested model modifications regarding (i) Akt contribution to IL-1-stimulated p38 MAPK activation and (ii) insignificant p38 MAPK activation in response to IL-6. In light of the presented results and in conjunction with the detailed model documentations, both models hold great potential for theoretical studies and practical applications.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2214:1/il1-signaling</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-08-26"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-05-18 13:30:40"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-08-26 10:05:13</field>
                    <field name="model_score">41.01010000000001</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2215">
                <name>Differentiation of T lymphocytes</name>
                <description>There is a vast amount of molecular information regarding the differentiation of T lymphocytes, in particular regarding in vitro experimental treatments that modify their differentiation process. This publicly available information was used to infer the regulatory network that controls the differentiation of T lymphocytes into CD4+ and CD8+ cells. Hereby we present a network that consists of 50 nodes and 97 regulatory interactions, representing the main signaling circuits established among molecules and molecular complexes regulating the differentiation of T cells. The network was converted into a continuous dynamical system in the form of a set of coupled ordinary differential equations, and its dynamical behavior was studied. With the aid of numerical methods, nine fixed point attractors were found for the dynamical system. These attractors correspond to the activation patterns observed experimentally for the following cell types: CD4?CD8?, CD4+CD8+, CD4+ naive, Th1, Th2, Th17, Treg, CD8+ naive, and CTL. Furthermore, the model is able to describe the differentiation process from the precursor CD4?CD8? to any of the effector types due to a specific series of extracellular signals.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2215:1/differentiation-of-t-lymphocytes</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-08-27"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-08-12 21:04:24"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-08-27 19:12:07</field>
                    <field name="model_score">13.3122</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="4775">
                <name>PC12 Cell Differentiation</name>
                <description>The nerve growth factor NGF has been shown to cause cell fate decisions toward either differentiation or proliferation depending on the relative activity of downstream pERK, pAKT, or pJNK signaling. However, how these protein signals are translated into and fed back from transcriptional activity to complete cellular differentiation over a time span of hours to days is still an open question. Comparing the time-resolved transcriptome response of NGF- or EGF-stimulated PC12 cells over 24 h in combination with protein and phenotype data we inferred a dynamic Boolean model capturing the temporal sequence of protein signaling, transcriptional response and subsequent autocrine feedback. Network topology was optimized by fitting the model to time-resolved transcriptome data under MEK, PI3K, or JNK inhibition. The integrated model confirmed the parallel use of MAPK/ERK, PI3K/AKT, and JNK/JUN for PC12 cell differentiation. Redundancy of cell signaling is demonstrated from the inhibition of the different MAPK pathways. As suggested in silico and confirmed in vitro, differentiation was substantially suppressed under JNK inhibition, yet delayed only under MEK/ERK inhibition. Most importantly, we found that positive transcriptional feedback induces bistability in the cell fate switch. De novo gene expression was necessary to activate autocrine feedback that caused Urokinase-Type Plasminogen Activator (uPA) Receptor signaling to perpetuate the MAPK activity, finally resulting in the expression of late, differentiation related genes. Thus, the cellular decision toward differentiation depends on the establishment of a transcriptome-induced positive feedback between protein signaling and gene expression thereby constituting a robust control between proliferation and differentiation.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#4775:1/pc12-cell-differentiation</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2016-08-17"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-03-03 13:57:42"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2016-08-17 11:57:51</field>
                    <field name="model_score">38.1004</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="4779">
                <name>Human Gonadal Sex Determination</name>
                <description>BACKGROUND: Gonadal sex determination (GSD) in humans is a complex biological process that takes place in early stages of embryonic development when the bipotential gonadal primordium (BGP) differentiates towards testes or ovaries. This decision is directed by one of two distinct pathways embedded in a GSD network activated in a population of coelomic epithelial cells, the Sertoli progenitor cells (SPC) and the granulosa progenitor cells (GPC). In males, the pathway is activated when the Sex-Determining Region Y (SRY) gene starts to be expressed, whereas in females the WNT4/ &#946;-catenin pathway promotes the differentiation of the GPCs towards ovaries. The interactions and dynamics of the elements that constitute the GSD network are poorly understood, thus our group is interested in inferring the general architecture of this network as well as modeling the dynamic behavior of a set of genes associated to this process under wild-type and mutant conditions. METHODS: We reconstructed the regulatory network of GSD with a set of genes directly associated with the process of differentiation from SPC and GPC towards Sertoli and granulosa cells, respectively. These genes are experimentally well-characterized and the effects of their deficiency have been clinically reported. We modeled this GSD network as a synchronous Boolean network model (BNM) and characterized its attractors under wild-type and mutant conditions. RESULTS: Three attractors with a clear biological meaning were found; one of them corresponding to the currently known gene expression pattern of Sertoli cells, the second correlating to the granulosa cells and, the third resembling a disgenetic gonad. CONCLUSIONS: The BNM of GSD that we present summarizes the experimental data on the pathways for Sertoli and granulosa establishment and sheds light on the overall behavior of a population of cells that differentiate within the developing gonad. With this model we propose a set of regulatory interactions needed to activate either the SRY or the WNT4/ &#946;-catenin pathway as well as their downstream targets, which are critical for further sex differentiation. In addition, we observed a pattern of altered regulatory interactions and their dynamics that lead to some disorders of sex development (DSD).</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#4779:1/human-gonadal-sex-determination</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2016-08-22"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-02-13 09:58:53"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2016-08-22 09:27:00</field>
                    <field name="model_score">24.8</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="4783">
                <name> IGVH mutations in chronic lymphocytic leukemia.</name>
                <description>BACKGROUND: Chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) is an incurable malignancy of mature B-lymphocytes, characterized as being a heterogeneous disease with variable clinical manifestation and survival. Mutational statuses of rearranged immunoglobulin heavy chain variable (IGVH) genes has been consider one of the most important prognostic factors in CLL, but despite of its proven value to predict the course of the disease, the regulatory programs and biological mechanisms responsible for the differences in clinical behavior are poorly understood. METHODS: In this study, (i) we performed differential gene expression analysis between the IGVH statuses using multiple and independent CLL cohorts in microarrays platforms, based on this information, (ii) we constructed a simplified protein-protein interaction (PPI) network and (iii) investigated its structure and critical genes. This provided the basis to (iv) develop a Boolean model, (v) infer biological regulatory mechanism and (vi) performed perturbation simulations in order to analyze the network in dynamic state. RESULTS: The result of topological analysis and the Boolean model showed that the transcriptional relationships of IGVH mutational status were determined by specific regulatory proteins (PTEN, FOS, EGR1, TNF, TGFBR3, IFGR2 and LPL). The dynamics of the network was controlled by attractors whose genes were involved in multiple and diverse signaling pathways, which may suggest a variety of mechanisms related with progression occurring over time in the disease. The overexpression of FOS and TNF fixed the fate of the system as they can activate important genes implicated in the regulation of process of adhesion, apoptosis, immune response, cell proliferation and other signaling pathways related with cancer. CONCLUSION: The differences in prognosis prediction of the IGVH mutational status are related with several regulatory hubs that determine the dynamic of the system.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#4783:1/-igvh-mutations-in-chronic-lymphocytic-leukemia.</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2016-08-23"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-03-15 11:01:19"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2016-08-23 16:35:33</field>
                    <field name="model_score">80.1007</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="1969">
                <name>HGF Signaling in Keratinocytes</name>
                <description>Cell migration is a complex process that is controlled through the time-sequential feedback regulation of protein signalling and gene regulation. Based on prior knowledge and own experimental data, we developed a large-scale dynamic network describing the onset and maintenance of hepatocyte growth factor-induced migration of primary human keratinocytes. We applied Boolean logic to capture the qualitative behaviour as well as short-and long-term dynamics of the complex signalling network involved in this process, comprising protein signalling, gene regulation and autocrine feedback. RESULTS: A Boolean model has been compiled from time-resolved transcriptome data and literature mining, incorporating the main pathways involved in migration from initial stimulation to phenotype progress. Steady-state analysis under different inhibition and stimulation conditions of known key molecules reproduces existing data and predicts novel interactions based on our own experiments. Model simulations highlight for the first time the necessity of a temporal sequence of initial, transient MET receptor (met proto-oncogene, hepatocyte growth factor receptor) and subsequent, continuous epidermal growth factor/integrin signalling to trigger and sustain migration by autocrine signalling that is integrated through the Focal adhesion kinase protein. We predicted in silico and verified in vitro that long-term cell migration is stopped if any of the two feedback loops are inhibited. AVAILABILITY: The network file for analysis with the R BoolNet library is available in the Supplementary Information. CONTACT: melanie.boerries@frias.uni-freiburg.de or hauke.busch@frias.uni-freiburg.de</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#1969:1/hgf-signaling-in-keratinocytes</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2012-09-12"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-07-12 15:48:28"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2012-09-12 22:28:20</field>
                    <field name="model_score">6.999999999999999</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2738">
                <name>HIV-1 interactions with T Cell Signalling Pathway</name>
                <description>Motivation: Human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1) hijacks host cellular processes to replicate within its host. Through interactions with host proteins, it perturbs and interrupts signaling pathways that alter key cellular functions. Although networks of viral&#8211;host interactions have been relatively well characterized, the dynamics of the perturbation process is poorly understood. Dynamic models of infection have the potential to provide insights into the HIV-1 host interaction.  Results: We employed a logical signal flow network to model the dynamic interactions between HIV-1 proteins and key human signal transduction pathways necessary for activation of CD4+ T lymphocytes. We integrated viral&#8211;host interaction and host signal transduction data into a dynamic logical model comprised of 137 nodes (16 HIV-1 and 121 human proteins) and 336 interactions collected from the HIV-1 Human Interaction Database. The model reproduced expected patterns of T-cell activation, co-stimulation and co-inhibition. After simulations, we identified 26 host cell factors, including MAPK1&amp;3, Ikkb-Ikky-Ikka and PKA, which contribute to the net activation or inhibition of viral proteins. Through in silico knockouts, the model identified a further nine host cell factors, including members of the PI3K signalling pathway that are essential to viral replication. Simulation results intersected with the findings of three siRNA gene knockout studies and identified potential drug targets. Our results demonstrate how viral infection causes the cell to lose control of its signalling system. Logical Boolean modelling therefore provides a useful approach for analysing the dynamics of host&#8211;viral interactions with potential applications for drug discovery.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2738:1/hiv1-interactions-with-t-cell-signalling-pathway</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2015-03-09"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2019-11-12 15:49:08"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2015-03-09 12:24:01</field>
                    <field name="model_score">45.7646</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="3506">
                <name>HH Pathway of Drosophila Signaling Pathways</name>
                <description>A limited number of signalling pathways are involved in the specification of cell fate during the development of all animals. Several of these pathways were originally identified in Drosophila. To clarify their roles, and possible cross-talk, we have built a logical model for the nine key signalling pathways recurrently used in metazoan development. In each case, we considered the associated ligands, receptors, signal transducers, modulators, and transcription factors reported in the literature. Implemented using the logical modelling software GINsim, the resulting models qualitatively recapitulate the main characteristics of each pathway, in wild type as well as in various mutant situations (e.g. loss-of-function or gain-of-function). These models constitute pluggable modules that can be used to assemble comprehensive models of complex developmental processes. Moreover, these models of Drosophila pathways could serve as scaffolds for more complicated models of orthologous mammalian pathways. Comprehensive model annotations and GINsim files are provided for each of the nine considered pathways.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#3506:1/hh-pathway-of-drosophila-signaling-pathways</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2015-01-21"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2015-01-21 15:24:47</field>
                    <field name="model_score">2.4000000000000004</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="3509">
                <name>B bronchiseptica and T retortaeformis coinfection</name>
                <description>Co-infections alter the host immune response but how the systemic and local processes at the site of infection interact is still unclear. The majority of studies on co-infections concentrate on one of the infecting species, an immune function or group of cells and often focus on the initial phase of the infection. Here, we used a combination of experiments and mathematical modelling to investigate the network of immune responses against single and co-infections with the respiratory bacterium Bordetella bronchiseptica and the gastrointestinal helminth Trichostrongylus retortaeformis. Our goal was to identify representative mediators and functions that could capture the essence of the host immune response as a whole, and to assess how their relative contribution dynamically changed over time and between single and co-infected individuals. Network-based discrete dynamic models of single infections were built using current knowledge of bacterial and helminth immunology; the two single infection models were combined into a co-infection model that was then verified by our empirical findings. Simulations showed that a T helper cell mediated antibody and neutrophil response led to phagocytosis and clearance of B. bronchiseptica from the lungs. This was consistent in single and co-infection with no significant delay induced by the helminth. In contrast, T. retortaeformis intensity decreased faster when co-infected with the bacterium. Simulations suggested that the robust recruitment of neutrophils in the co-infection, added to the activation of IgG and eosinophil driven reduction of larvae, which also played an important role in single infection, contributed to this fast clearance. Perturbation analysis of the models, through the knockout of individual nodes (immune cells), identified the cells critical to parasite persistence and clearance both in single and co-infections. Our integrated approach captured the within-host immuno-dynamics of bacteria-helminth infection and identified key components that can be crucial for explaining individual variability between single and co-infections in natural populations.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#3509:1/b-bronchiseptica-and-t-retortaeformis-coinfection</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-06-16"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-07-17 17:04:27"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-06-16 11:27:50</field>
                    <field name="model_score">17.910300000000003</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="3510">
                <name>FGF pathway of Drosophila Signalling Pathways</name>
                <description>Fig 3B from the following paper\r\nLogical modelling of Drosophila signalling pathways. Mbodj A, Junion G, Brun C, Furlong EE, Thieffry D. Mol Biosyst. 2013 Sep;9(9):2248-58. doi:10.1039/c3mb70187e</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#3510:1/fgf-pathway-of-drosophila-signalling-pathways</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2015-01-21"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2015-01-21 16:27:54</field>
                    <field name="model_score">5.1119</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="4790">
                <name>Fanconi anemia and checkpoint recovery</name>
                <description>The FA/BRCA pathway repairs DNA interstrand crosslinks. Mutations in this pathway cause Fanconi anemia (FA), a chromosome instability syndrome with bone marrow failure and cancer predisposition. Upon DNA damage, normal and FA cells inhibit the cell cycle progression, until the G2/M checkpoint is turned off by the checkpoint recovery, which becomes activated when the DNA damage has been repaired. Interestingly, highly damaged FA cells seem to override the G2/M checkpoint. In this study we explored with a Boolean network model and key experiments whether checkpoint recovery activation occurs in FA cells with extensive unrepaired DNA damage. Computational simulations suggested that in FA mutants checkpoint recovery activity inhibits the checkpoint components despite unrepaired DNA damage, a behavior that we did not observed in wild-type simulations. This result implies that FA cells would eventually reenter the cell cycle after a DNA damage induced G2/M checkpoint arrest, but before the damage has been fixed. We observed that FA-A cells activate the G2/M checkpoint and arrest in G2 phase, but eventually reach mitosis and divide with unrepaired DNA damage, thus resolving the initial checkpoint arrest. Based on our model result we look for ectopic activity of checkpoint recovery components. We found that checkpoint recovery components, such as PLK1, are expressed to a similar extent as normal undamaged cells do, even though FA-A cells harbor highly damaged DNA. Our results show that FA cells, despite extensive DNA damage, do not loss the capacity to express the transcriptional and protein components of checkpoint recovery that might eventually allow their division with unrepaired DNA damage. This might allow cell survival but increases the genomic instability inherent to FA individuals and promotes cancer.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#4790:1/fanconi-anemia-and-checkpoint-recovery</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2016-08-28"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-02-10 13:29:15"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2016-08-28 19:07:05</field>
                    <field name="model_score">27.3608</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="3511">
                <name>Glucose Repression Signaling 2009</name>
                <description>Background In the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae, the presence of high levels of glucose leads to an array of down-regulatory effects known as glucose repression. This process is complex due to the presence of feedback loops and crosstalk between different pathways, complicating the use of intuitive approaches to analyze the system.  Results We established a logical model of yeast glucose repression, formalized as a hypergraph. The model was constructed based on verified regulatory interactions and it includes 50 gene transcripts, 22 proteins, 5 metabolites and 118 hyperedges. We computed the logical steady states of all nodes in the network in order to simulate wildtype and deletion mutant responses to different sugar availabilities. Evaluation of the model predictive power was achieved by comparing changes in the logical state of gene nodes with transcriptome data. Overall, we observed 71% true predictions, and analyzed sources of errors and discrepancies for the remaining.  Conclusion Though the binary nature of logical (Boolean) models entails inherent limitations, our model constitutes a primary tool for storing regulatory knowledge, searching for incoherencies in hypotheses and evaluating the effect of deleting regulatory elements involved in glucose repression.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#3511:1/glucose-repression-signaling-2009</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2014-10-31"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-10-16 12:31:16"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2014-10-31 15:29:36</field>
                    <field name="model_score">29.7741</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="3512">
                <name>Oxidative Stress Pathway</name>
                <description>Oxidative stress is a consequence of normal and abnormal cellular metabolism and is linked to the development of human diseases. The effective functioning of the pathway responding to oxidative stress protects the cellular DNA against oxidative damage; conversely the failure of the oxidative stress response mechanism can induce aberrant cellular behavior leading to diseases such as neurodegenerative disorders and cancer. Thus, understanding the normal signaling present in oxidative stress response pathways and determining possible signaling alterations leading to disease could provide us with useful pointers for therapeutic purposes. Using knowledge of oxidative stress response pathways from the literature, we developed a Boolean network model whose simulated behavior is consistent with earlier experimental observations from the literature. Concatenating the oxidative stress response pathways with the PI3-Kinase-Akt pathway, the oxidative stress is linked to the phenotype of apoptosis, once again through a Boolean network model. Furthermore, we present an approach for pinpointing possible fault locations by using temporal variations in the oxidative stress input and observing the resulting deviations in the apoptotic signature from the normally predicted pathway. Such an approach could potentially form the basis for designing more effective combination therapies against complex diseases such as cancer. RESULTS: In this paper, we have developed a Boolean network model for the oxidative stress response. This model was developed based on pathway information from the current literature pertaining to oxidative stress. Where applicable, the behaviour predicted by the model is in agreement with experimental observations from the published literature. We have also linked the oxidative stress response to the phenomenon of apoptosis via the PI3k/Akt pathway. CONCLUSIONS: It is our hope that some of the additional predictions here, such as those pertaining to the oscillatory behaviour of certain genes in the presence of oxidative stress, will be experimentally validated in the near future. Of course, it should be pointed out that the theoretical procedure presented here for pinpointing fault locations in a biological network with feedback will need to be further simplified before it can be even considered for practical biological validation.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#3512:1/oxidative-stress-pathway</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-06-01"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-07-14 16:45:54"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-06-01 14:23:34</field>
                    <field name="model_score">31.0317</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="3521">
                <name>CD4 T cell signaling</name>
                <description>Caveolin-1 (CAV1) is a vital scaffold protein heterogeneously expressed in both healthy and malignant tissue. We focus on the role of CAV1 when overexpressed in T-cell leukemia. Previously, we have shown that CAV1 is involved in cell-to-cell communication, cellular proliferation, and immune synapse formation; however, the molecular mechanisms have not been elucidated. We hypothesize that the role of CAV1 in immune synapse formation contributes to immune regulation during leukemic progression, thereby warranting studies of the role of CAV1 in CD4(+) T-cells in relation to antigen-presenting cells. To address this need, we developed a computational model of a CD4(+) immune effector T-cell to mimic cellular dynamics and molecular signaling under healthy and immunocompromised conditions (i.e., leukemic conditions). Using the Cell Collective computational modeling software, the CD4(+) T-cell model was constructed and simulated under CAV1 (+/+), CAV1 (+/-), and CAV1 (-/-) conditions to produce a hypothetical immune response. This model allowed us to predict and examine the heterogeneous effects and mechanisms of CAV1 in silico. Experimental results indicate a signature of molecules involved in cellular proliferation, cell survival, and cytoskeletal rearrangement that were highly affected by CAV1 knock out. With this comprehensive model of a CD4(+) T-cell, we then validated in vivo protein expression levels. Based on this study, we modeled a CD4(+) T-cell, manipulated gene expression in immunocompromised versus competent settings, validated these manipulations in an in vivo murine model, and corroborated acute T-cell leukemia gene expression profiles in human beings. Moreover, we can model an immunocompetent versus an immunocompromised microenvironment to better understand how signaling is regulated in patients with leukemia.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#3521:1/cd4-t-cell-signaling</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-12-05"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-12-05 20:19:58</field>
                    <field name="model_score">6.8973</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="4837">
                <name>Arabidopsis thaliana Cell Cycle</name>
                <description>Cell cycle control is fundamental in eukaryotic development. Several modeling efforts have been used to integrate the complex network of interacting molecular components involved in cell cycle dynamics. In this paper, we aimed at recovering the regulatory logic upstream of previously known components of cell cycle control, with the aim of understanding the mechanisms underlying the emergence of the cyclic behavior of such components. We focus on Arabidopsis thaliana, but given that many components of cell cycle regulation are conserved among eukaryotes, when experimental data for this system was not available, we considered experimental results from yeast and animal systems. We are proposing a Boolean gene regulatory network (GRN) that converges into only one robust limit cycle attractor that closely resembles the cyclic behavior of the key cell-cycle molecular components and other regulators considered here. We validate the model by comparing our in silico configurations with data from loss- and gain-of-function mutants, where the endocyclic behavior also was recovered. Additionally, we approximate a continuous model and recovered the temporal periodic expression profiles of the cell-cycle molecular components involved, thus suggesting that the single limit cycle attractor recovered with the Boolean model is not an artifact of its discrete and synchronous nature, but rather an emergent consequence of the inherent characteristics of the regulatory logic proposed here. This dynamical model, hence provides a novel theoretical framework to address cell cycle regulation in plants, and it can also be used to propose novel predictions regarding cell cycle regulation in other eukaryotes.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#4837:1/arabidopsis-thaliana-cell-cycle</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2016-09-12"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-10-13 13:09:34"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2016-09-12 08:51:56</field>
                    <field name="model_score">22.3001</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="6885">
                <name>Regulation of the L-arabinose operon of Escherichia coli.</name>
                <description>The lactose operon in Escherichia coli was the first known gene regulatory network, and it is frequently used as a prototype for new modeling paradigms. Historically, many of these modeling frameworks use differential equations. More recently, Stigler and Veliz-Cuba proposed a Boolean network model that captures the bistability of the system and all of the biological steady states. In this paper, we model the wellknown arabinose operon in E. coli with a Boolean network. This has several complex features not found in the lac operon, such as a protein that is both an activator and repressor, a DNA looping mechanism for gene repression, and the lack of inducer exclusion by glucose. For 11 out of 12 choices of initial conditions, we use computational algebra and Sage to verify that the state space contains a single fixed point that correctly matches the biology. The final initial condition, medium levels of arabinose and no glucose, successfully predicts the system&#8217;s bistability. Finally, we compare the state space under synchronous and asynchronous update, and see that the former has several artificial cycles that go away under a general asynchronous update.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#6885:1/regulation-of-the-larabinose-operon-of-escherichia-coli.</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2017-03-12"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-07-18 15:44:25"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2017-03-12 11:02:47</field>
                    <field name="model_score">3.5</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="7916">
                <name>Aurora Kinase A in Neuroblastoma</name>
                <description>Aurora Kinase A (AURKA) is often overexpressed in neuroblastoma (NB) with poor outcome. The causes of AURKA overexpression in NB are unknown. Here, we describe a gene regulatory network consisting of core regulators of AURKA protein expression and activation during mitosis to identify potential causes. This network was transformed to a dynamic Boolean model. Simulated activation of the serine/threonine protein kinase Greatwall (GWL, encoded by MASTL) that attenuates the pivotal AURKA inhibitor PP2A, predicted stabilization of AURKA. Consistent with this notion, gene set enrichment analysis showed enrichment of mitotic spindle assembly genes and MYCN target genes in NB with high GWL/MASTL expression. In line with the prediction of GWL/MASTL enhancing AURKA, elevated expression of GWL/MASTL was associated with NB risk factors and poor survival of patients. These results establish Boolean network modeling of oncogenic pathways in NB as a useful means for guided discovery in this enigmatic cancer.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#7916:1/aurora-kinase-a-in-neuroblastoma</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2017-04-20"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2018-04-23 08:16:31"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2017-04-20 16:52:20</field>
                    <field name="model_score">24.960500000000003</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="1776">
                <name>ErbB (1-4) Receptor Signaling</name>
                <description>This is a comprehensive, multi-scale model of ErbB receptor signal transduction in human mammary epithelial cells. This model, constructed manually from published biochemical literature, consists of 245 nodes representing proteins and their post-translational modifications sites, and over 1,000 biochemical interactions. The model also contains a number of commonly expressed receptor signaling pathways, including ErbB (1-4), EGFR endocytosis and recycling, G-protein-coupled receptor (alpha i, alpha q, alpha 12/13, and alpha s ligands), integrin, e-cadherin, and stress pathways.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#1776:1/erbb-(14)-receptor-signaling</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2012-04-10"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2012-04-10 12:46:49</field>
                    <field name="model_score">16.5239</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="1778">
                <name>FA BRCA pathway</name>
                <description> MOTIVATION: Fanconi anemia (FA) is a chromosomal instability syndrome originated by inherited mutations that impair the Fanconi Anemia/Breast Cancer (FA/BRCA) pathway, which is committed to the repair of DNA interstrand cross-links (ICLs). The disease displays increased spontaneous chromosomal aberrations and hypersensitivity to agents that create DNA interstrand cross-links. In spite of DNA damage, FA/BRCA-deficient cells are able to progress throughout the cell cycle, probably due to the activity of alternative DNA repair pathways, or due to defects in the checkpoints that monitor DNA integrity. RESULTS: We propose a Boolean network model of the FA/BRCA pathway, Checkpoint proteins and some alternative DNA repair pathways. To our knowledge, this is the largest network model incorporating a DNA repair pathway. Our model is able to simulate the ICL repair process mediated by the FA/BRCA pathway, the activation of Checkpoint proteins observed by recurrent DNA damage, as well as the repair of DNA double-strand breaks and DNA adducts. We generated a series of simulations for mutants, some of which have never been reported and thus constitute predictions about the function of the FA/BRCA pathway. Finally, our model suggests alternative DNA repair pathways that become active whenever the FA/BRCA pathway is defective.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#1778:1/fa-brca-pathway</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2012-04-13"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2012-04-13 12:45:01</field>
                    <field name="model_score">17.4304</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="4850">
                <name> Bortezomib Responses in U266 Human Myeloma Cells</name>
                <description>Systems models of biological networks show promise for informing drug target selection/qualification, identifying lead compounds and factors regulating disease progression, rationalizing combinatorial regimens, and explaining sources of intersubject variability and adverse drug reactions. However, most models of biological systems are qualitative and are not easily coupled with dynamical models of drug exposure-response relationships. In this proof-of-concept study, logic-based modeling of signal transduction pathways in U266 multiple myeloma (MM) cells is used to guide the development of a simple dynamical model linking bortezomib exposure to cellular outcomes. Bortezomib is a commonly used first-line agent in MM treatment; however, knowledge of the signal transduction pathways regulating bortezomib-mediated cell cytotoxicity is incomplete. A Boolean network model of 66 nodes was constructed that includes major survival and apoptotic pathways and was updated using responses to several chemical probes. Simulated responses to bortezomib were in good agreement with experimental data, and a reduction algorithm was used to identify key signaling proteins. Bortezomib-mediated apoptosis was not associated with suppression of nuclear factor &#954;B (NF&#954;B) protein inhibition in this cell line, which contradicts a major hypothesis of bortezomib pharmacodynamics. A pharmacodynamic model was developed that included three critical proteins (phospho-NF&#954;B, BclxL, and cleaved poly (ADP ribose) polymerase). Model-fitted protein dynamics and cell proliferation profiles agreed with experimental data, and the model-predicted IC50 (3.5 nM) is comparable to the experimental value (1.5 nM). The cell-based pharmacodynamic model successfully links bortezomib exposure to MM cellular proliferation via protein dynamics, and this model may show utility in exploring bortezomib-based combination regimens.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#4850:1/-bortezomib-responses-in-u266-human-myeloma-cells</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2016-09-14"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2018-03-27 15:46:39"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2016-09-14 09:01:51</field>
                    <field name="model_score">26.514700000000005</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="2035">
                <name>Cortical Area Development</name>
                <description>The cerebral cortex is divided into many functionally distinct areas. The emergence of these areas during neural development is dependent on the expression patterns of several genes. Along the anterior-posterior axis, gradients of Fgf8, Emx2, Pax6, Coup-tfi, and Sp8 play a particularly strong role in specifying areal identity. However, our understanding of the regulatory interactions between these genes that lead to their confinement to particular spatial patterns is currently qualitative and incomplete. We therefore used a computational model of the interactions between these five genes to determine which interactions, and combinations of interactions, occur in networks that reproduce the anterior-posterior expression patterns observed experimentally. The model treats expression levels as Boolean, reflecting the qualitative nature of the expression data currently available. We simulated gene expression patterns created by all possible networks containing the five genes of interest. We found that only of these networks were able to reproduce the experimentally observed expression patterns. These networks all lacked certain interactions and combinations of interactions including auto-regulation and inductive loops. Many higher order combinations of interactions also never appeared in networks that satisfied our criteria for good performance. While there was remarkable diversity in the structure of the networks that perform well, an analysis of the probability of each interaction gave an indication of which interactions are most likely to be present in the gene network regulating cortical area development. We found that in general, repressive interactions are much more likely than inductive ones, but that mutually repressive loops are not critical for correct network functioning. Overall, our model illuminates the design principles of the gene network regulating cortical area development, and makes novel predictions that can be tested experimentally.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#2035:1/cortical-area-development</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2013-03-17"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2016-01-22 07:08:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2013-03-17 12:46:02</field>
                    <field name="model_score">18.3</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="7926">
                <name>Iron acquisition and oxidative stress response in aspergillus fumigatus.</name>
                <description>Aspergillus fumigatus is a ubiquitous airborne fungal pathogen that presents a life-threatening health risk to individuals with weakened immune systems. A. fumigatus pathogenicity depends on its ability to acquire iron from the host and to resist host-generated oxidative stress. Gaining a deeper understanding of the molecular mechanisms governing A. fumigatus iron acquisition and oxidative stress response may ultimately help to improve the diagnosis and treatment of invasive aspergillus infections. This study follows a systems biology approach to investigate how adaptive behaviors emerge from molecular interactions underlying A. fumigatus iron regulation and oxidative stress response. We construct a Boolean network model from known interactions and simulate how changes in environmental iron and superoxide levels affect network dynamics. We propose rules for linking long term model behavior to qualitative estimates of cell growth and cell death. These rules are used to predict phenotypes of gene deletion strains. The model is validated on the basis of its ability to reproduce literature data not used in model generation. The model reproduces gene expression patterns in experimental time course data when A. fumigatus is switched from a low iron to a high iron environment. In addition, the model is able to accurately represent the phenotypes of many knockout strains under varying iron and superoxide conditions. Model simulations support the hypothesis that intracellular iron regulates A. fumigatus transcription factors, SreA and HapX, by a post-translational, rather than transcriptional, mechanism. Finally, the model predicts that blocking siderophore-mediated iron uptake reduces resistance to oxidative stress. This indicates that combined targeting of siderophore-mediated iron uptake and the oxidative stress response network may act synergistically to increase fungal cell killing.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#7926:1/iron-acquisition-and-oxidative-stress-response-in-aspergillus-fumigatus.</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2017-04-24"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-05-19 13:14:25"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2017-04-24 10:44:42</field>
                    <field name="model_score">17.7</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="4601">
                <name>Colitis-associated colon cancer</name>
                <description>This model looks at the development of colitis-associated colon cancer in order investigate the mechanism behind inflammation-associated tumorigenesis. Dynamic simulations reveal that P53, MDM2, and AKT may constitute a core network responsible for the malignant transformation of colon epithelial cells in a pro-tumor inflammatory environment. This model can aid in furthering mechanistic studies on colitis-associated colon cancer in addition to identifying novel cancer therapies.  </description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#4601:1/colitisassociated-colon-cancer</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2016-06-17"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-01-30 13:44:46"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2016-06-17 10:33:38</field>
                    <field name="model_score">82.40960000000001</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="8186">
                <name>Lymphoid and myeloid cell specification and transdifferentiation</name>
                <description>Blood cells are derived from a common set of hematopoietic stem cells, which differentiate into more specific progenitors of the myeloid and lymphoid lineages, ultimately leading to differentiated cells. This developmental process is controlled by a complex regulatory network involving cytokines and their receptors, transcription factors, and chromatin remodelers. Using public data and data from our own molecular genetic experiments (quantitative PCR, Western blot, EMSA) or genome-wide assays (RNA-sequencing, ChIP-sequencing), we have assembled a comprehensive regulatory network encompassing the main transcription factors and signaling components involved in myeloid and lymphoid development. Focusing on B-cell and macrophage development, we defined a qualitative dynamical model recapitulating cytokine-induced differentiation of common progenitors, the effect of various reported gene knockdowns, and the reprogramming of pre-B cells into macrophages induced by the ectopic expression of specific transcription factors. The resulting network model can be used as a template for the integration of new hematopoietic differentiation and transdifferentiation data to foster our understanding of lymphoid/myeloid cell-fate decisions.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#8186:1/lymphoid-and-myeloid-cell-specification-and-transdifferentiation</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2017-06-16"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-07-25 20:46:31"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2017-06-16 14:30:46</field>
                    <field name="model_score">32.4108</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="5884">
                <name>Tumour Cell Invasion and Migration</name>
                <description>Understanding the etiology of metastasis is very important in clinical perspective, since it is estimated that metastasis accounts for 90% of cancer patient mortality. Metastasis results from a sequence of multiple steps including invasion and migration. The early stages of metastasis are tightly controlled in normal cells and can be drastically affected by malignant mutations; therefore, they might constitute the principal determinants of the overall metastatic rate even if the later stages take long to occur. To elucidate the role of individual mutations or their combinations affecting the metastatic development, a logical model has been constructed that recapitulates published experimental results of known gene perturbations on local invasion and migration processes, and predict the effect of not yet experimentally assessed mutations. The model has been validated using experimental data on transcriptome dynamics following TGF-&#946;-dependent induction of Epithelial to Mesenchymal Transition in lung cancer cell lines. A method to associate gene expression profiles with different stable state solutions of the logical model has been developed for that purpose. In addition, we have systematically predicted alleviating (masking) and synergistic pairwise genetic interactions between the genes composing the model with respect to the probability of acquiring the metastatic phenotype. We focused on several unexpected synergistic genetic interactions leading to theoretically very high metastasis probability. Among them, the synergistic combination of Notch overexpression and p53 deletion shows one of the strongest effects, which is in agreement with a recent published experiment in a mouse model of gut cancer. The mathematical model can recapitulate experimental mutations in both cell line and mouse models. Furthermore, the model predicts new gene perturbations that affect the early steps of metastasis underlying potential intervention points for innovative therapeutic strategies in oncology.</description>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#5884:1/tumour-cell-invasion-and-migration</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2017-02-01"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2017-04-28 14:44:10"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">None</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">1</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2017-02-01 12:35:02</field>
                    <field name="model_score">32.464600000000004</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="36604">
                <name>Signaling Pathway for Butanol Production in Clostridium beijerinckii NRRL B-598</name>
                <description/>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#36604:2/signaling-pathway-for-butanol-production-in-clostridium-beijerinckii-nrrl-b598</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2019-02-05"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2019-04-03 08:30:36"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">1</field>
                    <field name="version_name">1.0</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">2</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2019-03-21 08:45:31</field>
                    <field name="model_score">59.4487</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        

            <entry id="36604">
                <name>Signaling Pathway for Butanol Production in Clostridium beijerinckii NRRL B-598</name>
                <description/>
                <url>https://cellcollective.org/#36604:2/signaling-pathway-for-butanol-production-in-clostridium-beijerinckii-nrrl-b598</url>
                <contact/>
                <dates>
                    <date type="created" value="2019-03-21"/>
                    <date type="last_modified" value="2019-04-03 08:30:36"/>
                </dates>
                <additional_fields>
                    <field name="version_id">2</field>
                    <field name="version_name">1.1</field>
                    <field name="version_description">None</field>
                    <field name="default_version">2</field>
                    <field name="model_created">2019-03-21 08:45:31</field>
                    <field name="model_score">59.4487</field>
                </additional_fields>
            </entry>        
    </entries>
</dataset>